エホバの証人の統治体と
On behalf of the Governing Body
and all of those working
世界本部で働く兄弟姉妹たち
全員を代表して
at the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
it’s my pleasure to welcome you
皆さんを2022
「平和をつくる」地区大会に
to the 2022 “Pursue Peace”! Convention.
心から歓迎いたします
JW Broadcasting®の
特別版として
These convention segments,
which constitute special editions
今月と来月お送りする
この大会のプログラムは
of JW Broadcasting® this month and next,
have been translated
into more than 500 languages.
世界各地の500以上の
言語に翻訳されました
1日目の主題は
The scripture theme
for this session and the next
詩編 29:11に基づく
is Psalm 29:11:
「エホバはその民に平和を与えて
祝福する」というものです
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
As you watch
the following music-video presentation,
次のミュージックビデオから
分かるように
私たちはエホバの創造物を観察し
notice the peace we find
エホバの言葉である聖書を読み
by observing Jehovah’s creations,
reading his Word,
エホバからの良い知らせを
伝えることによって
and sharing his message with others.
平和を味わえます
Please enjoy the presentation.
どうぞビデオをお楽しみください
エホバの証人の
「平和をつくる」地区大会の
We are delighted you could join us
for the opening session
最初の部を視聴してくださって
いることをうれしく思います
of the “Pursue Peace”! Convention
of Jehovah’s Witnesses!
Let’s sing together song number 86, entitled
ご一緒に86番の「エホバの教えを
受けましょう」という歌を歌いましょう
“We Must Be Taught.”
That’s song number 86.
歌の番号は86番です
神はどのような平和を
What kind of peace does God give,
誰に与えてくださるのでしょうか
and to whom does he give it?
こうした点について エホバの証人の
統治体のスティーブン・レット兄弟が
Brother Stephen Lett, a member
of the Governing Body of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
will answer these questions
in the opening talk of our program.
大会の最初の話の中で
取り上げてくださいます
Please pay close attention
as he develops the theme
この話に注意深く耳を傾けましょう
主題は
「エホバは『平和を与える神』」です
“Jehovah Is ‘the God Who Gives Peace.’”
皆さんを心から歓迎し
It is my great pleasure
to warmly welcome all of you
このようにごあいさつしたいと思います
and to say, “Shalom.”
「シャーローム」
「シャーローム」とは何でしょうか
Why is saying that appropriate?
Well, shalom {
これは「平和」を意味するヘブライ語で
この言葉は聖書の中に
200回以上出てきます
and it occurs over 200 times in the Bible.
When it’s used as a greeting
(just as I used it),
あいさつとして使う場合には
こういう意味になります
it means: “May you have peace.”
「あなたに平和がありますように」
それで この言葉を使って 皆さんを
So, what could be a more appropriate way
to greet all of you at the start
エホバの証人の「平和をつくる」
地区大会に歓迎できることを
of this “Pursue Peace”!
Convention of Jehovah’s Witnesses!
とてもうれしく思います
We are very pleased that you’re with us,
この大会を楽しみにして
おられたと思いますが
and we assure you
that you will not be disappointed.
その期待は決して裏切られません
3日間のプログラムを通して
たくさんのことを学べます
To the contrary, you’ll be glad you were able
to devote three days to learning
what the Bible says
どうすれば生活のあらゆる面で
平和を味わえるかについて
about how to gain and maintain peace
聖書の大切な教えが
さまざまな角度から取り上げられます
in all areas of your life.
ではまず 私たち皆を
But now let’s begin
by talking about the Person
この大会に招待してくださった方に
ついて少し考えましょう エホバです
who has drawn us all together
for this convention—Jehovah.
And how we delight in talking
素晴らしい天のお父さんについて
考えられるのは うれしいことですね
about our marvelous heavenly Father!
Philippians 4:9
フィリピ 4:9で エホバは
「平和の神」と呼ばれています
calls Jehovah “the God of peace.”
Now, it’s true
that he possesses many qualities
エホバには愛 公正 知恵 力など
—love, justice, wisdom, power—
際立った面がたくさんありますが
but he also possesses the quality of peace.
平和も素晴らしい面の1つです
エホバは平和を愛する穏やかな方です
If you think about it,
he is at peace with himself,
天使たちや忠実な人間とも
平和な関係にあります
at peace with angels,
at peace with faithful humans.
Yes, he is “the God of peace.”
確かに平和の神だと言えます
では エホバは私たちも平和を味わえる
ようにしてくださるのでしょうか
But now here’s a question:
Does Jehovah keep this peace to himself?
Well, let’s get the answer
at Romans chapter 15.
ローマ 15章に答えがあります
ローマ 15:33を
ご一緒に読んでみることにしましょう
Romans chapter 15
and please let’s read verse 33:
こうあります 「平和を与える神が
“May the God who gives peace
皆さんと共にいてくださいますように
アーメン」
be with all of you. Amen.”
エホバは平和を惜しみなく
与えてくださいます
So he generously gives this peace,
as we’ll be discussing.
In fact, he gives
“every good gift and every perfect present,”
ヤコブ 1:17にあるように
あらゆる「良い贈り物」を
与えてくださいますが
according to James 1:17.
And one of his finest presents
is the gift of peace.
その中に平和が含まれています
But now here’s another question:
では エホバが与えてくださる平和とは
どういうものなのでしょうか
What kind of peace does Jehovah give?
Well, many equate peace
多くの人は平和と聞くと
with freedom from conflict
and strife in one’s life.
争いがない状態を思い浮かべるでしょう
でも神からの平和はそれ以上のものです
But the peace Jehovah gives
is a lot more than that.
The peace that only Jehovah can supply
エホバしか与えることができない
平和には
この上ない安心感や
brings in feelings of safety,
穏やかで幸せな気持ちが含まれています
security, well-being.
そのエホバからの平和について
This Jehovah-given peace
is described very nicely
in Philippians chapter 4.
フィリピ 4章に書かれているので
そこを見てみましょう
Let’s go there.
フィリピ 4:6, 7
Philippians chapter 4 beginning in verse 6:
「何も心配せず いつでも祈り
“Do not be anxious over anything,
“but in everything by prayer and supplication
祈願を捧げ 感謝しつつ 願いを
神に知っていただくようにしましょう
“along with thanksgiving,
“let your petitions be made known to God;
そうすれば 神からの平和が
キリスト・イエスを通して
皆さんの心と考えを守ります
“and the peace of God
that surpasses all understanding
“will guard your hearts
and your mental powers
その平和は人間の理解を
はるかに超えています」
by means of Christ Jesus.”
So notice that Jehovah is saying:
“Do not be anxious over anything.”
ここでエホバは 何も心配
しないようにと言っています
Would Jehovah tell us to do something
これは 一切心配してはならない
という意味でしょうか
that was impossible for us to do?
No.
いいえ ここでエホバが
私たちに注意してほしいのは
But, obviously, he’s talking about not being
心配し過ぎないことです
overly anxious.
適度な心配はためになることがあります
Controlled anxiety
can actually be beneficial.
It can move us to show concern for others.
それによって他の人のことを気遣えたり
与えられた務めを果たせるように
一生懸命努力できたりすることでしょう
It can motivate us to work enthusiastically
to accomplish an assignment.
But now, what about excessive,
uncontrolled anxiety?
でも 心配し過ぎるとどうでしょうか
Well, that can lead to physical problems.
体や精神に悪影響があります
Depression can be crippling,
体力や気力が奪われて
弱ってしまうかもしれません
debilitating, enfeebling.
では 何も心配しない
つまり心配し過ぎないためには
But now, how can we avoid
being overly anxious over anything?
どうしたらいいのでしょうか
The answer is given in the next words
of Philippians 4:6, 7.
フィリピ 4:6, 7の続きの部分に
答えがあります
エホバは 心配しないようにと
言ってから 何と述べているでしょうか
After telling us not to be anxious,
Jehovah gives the antidote.
He basically tells us to pray,
supplicate, and petition him,
エホバに祈り 祈願や請願をするなら
「神からの平和」が得られると
言っています
and we will get that “peace of God.”
では聖句の最後の部分は
どういう意味でしょうか
But now, what does the scripture mean
when it says that this ‘peace of God
「［神から］の平和は人間の理解を
はるかに超えています」とあります
surpasses all understanding’?
これは 神からの平和が
あまりに素晴らしいので
Well, we could say
that it’s so amazing and so powerful
that we limited humans
cannot fully understand it.
人間には十分に理解できない
ということです
私たちには説明が
つかないこともあります
It defies logic from a human standpoint.
心配や不安で頭がいっぱいになって
Our hearts and minds may be filled
with so much worry, fear, anxiety
八方ふさがりのように思える時に
that we see no way out, but we beg Jehovah
エホバに「平和を与えてください」と
お願いするとします
for the peace that he can supply.
And then what happens?
どうなるでしょうか
Our minds and hearts
are amazingly filled with calmness,
とても不思議に思えるほど
穏やかで落ち着いた
security, tranquility.
平和な状態になることがあります
ロレインという若い姉妹は
Loraine, a young girl
母親をがんで亡くした時のことについて
こう言っています
whose mother was dying
of cancer, said this:
「わたしが部屋にいる時に
母は息を引き取りました
“I was in the room
when my mother took her last breath.
すぐにわたしは ⋯⋯耐え［ら］れる
強さをお与えください と
“I . . . asked Jehovah
to give me the strength
“to endure and to get through this.
エホバに祈りました
I immediately felt the peace of God.”
するとすぐに神の平和を感じました」
では 7節にある「神からの平和が⋯⋯
But now, what is meant by the expression
“the peace of God . . .
will guard your hearts
皆さんの心と考えを守［る］」とは
どういうことでしょうか
and your mental powers”?
ここで「守る」と訳されている
ギリシャ語は軍事用語で
Well, the Greek word translated “guard”
is a military term
that evokes a mental picture
兵士たちが昼も夜も見張りをしている
様子を思い起こさせます
of soldiers
maintaining a day-and-night watch.
In the same way,
神からの平和は いわば兵士のように
this peace of God
can act like a 24-hour guard
私たちの心と考えを
24時間体制で守ってくれて
over our hearts and mental powers
穏やかで平和な状態を
保てるように助けてくれます
—keeping them calm, secure, and tranquil.
Now, here’s a question:
ここで考えたいのは この素晴らしい
神からの平和を与えてもらうために
What is the key ingredient
to our being able to receive
this miraculous peace of God?
欠かせないのはどんなことか
という点です
答えは エホバとの親しい友情を
築いていることです
The answer:
Having a close friendship with Jehovah.
The apostle Paul
experienced firsthand many times
使徒パウロが何度も経験したように
神からの平和は個々の状況に
左右されるものではありません
that having inner peace depends,
not on circumstances,
but, rather, on a close,
personal relationship with Jehovah.
エホバとの親しい関係があれば
得られるものです
例えば ある時パウロとシラスは
For example, on one occasion
because Paul and Silas boldly preached,
伝道をしてひどい目に遭いました
2人とも服を剝ぎ取られ
they had their garments ripped off of them.
They were beaten—many blows with rods.
棒で何度も打ちたたかれた後
They were thrown into the inner prison.
牢屋に入れられました
さらに足かせもはめられました
Their feet were fastened in stocks.
But in the middle of the night,
でも 真夜中にパウロとシラスは
何をしましたか
what did Paul and Silas begin to do?
They began to pray
and sing songs of praise to Jehovah.
祈ったり 歌でエホバを
賛美したりしました
In amazement,
他の囚人は驚きながら
祈りや歌を聞いていました
all the other prisoners
were listening to them.
So obviously, their very,
very unfavorable circumstances
ですから パウロとシラスは
とてもひどい状況に置かれていたものの
had not robbed them
of their precious peace of God.
神からの平和を味わって
いたことが分かります
この例から貴重な教訓を
学ぶことができます
So let’s learn
this valuable lesson from Paul and Silas.
Having the peace of God
神からの平和は 個々の状況に
左右されるものではありません
is not dependent on our circumstances,
but it is dependent
エホバとの親しい関係があれば
on having a close,
personal relationship with Jehovah.
いつでも与えてもらうことが
できるものなのです
ここまでで エホバが平和の神で
平和を与えてくださること
Thus far, we’ve discussed how Jehovah
is the God of peace who gives peace,
また それがどんな平和かを考えました
and we’ve talked
about what kind of peace he gives.
But now we ask,
では 平和を与えてもらうために
何が必要かをさらに考えましょう
To whom does Jehovah give peace?
The simple answer is,
エホバが平和を与えるのは
Jehovah gives peace
to those who draw close to him
ご自分との絆を強めようと努力し
導きに従いたいと思う人たちです
and want to follow his guidance.
ですから 神からの平和を頂くには
So receiving peace from Jehovah starts
エホバの道徳基準に従って
with living a clean life,
清く正しい生き方をする必要があります
following Jehovah’s
righteous moral standards.
世の中の多くの人は
Many people in Satan’s world, as you know,
どんな生き方をしたとしても
believe that God will accept them as they are
神に受け入れてもらえると思っています
神が基準を下げてくれると
思っているのです
—that God in effect
will lower his standard to accommodate them.
Can you imagine such pride?
それは間違っています
That would be like a pot
telling its maker, the potter,
あたかも器が 自分を作った陶芸家に
自分の使い方について指図し
how the pot must be used,
自分の要求を無理やり受け入れさせよう
としているかのようです
and the potter must accept this,
whether he likes it or not.
それは受け入れられませんね
Well, we know
it doesn’t work that way, does it?
人間がエホバの基準に合わせるべきです
We have to come up
to Jehovah’s righteous standards.
Now, he’ll help us, but we do the changing
変わるべきなのは私たちの方で
—certainly not Jehovah.
エホバではありません
興味深いことに ヤコブ 3:17には
このように書かれています
Interestingly, James 3:17
says that “the wisdom from above
「天からの知恵を持つ人は
“is first of all pure,
第一に清く 次いで平和を求め［る］」
then peaceable.”
So if we want peace from Jehovah
ですから 神からの平和を
与えていただくためには
that will result in peaceful lives,
エホバの道徳基準に従って
清くなければなりません
we must be pure
according to Jehovah’s moral standards.
イザヤ 48:22でエホバは
このように言っています
Isaiah 48:22 reads:
“‘There is no peace,’
says Jehovah, ‘for the wicked.’”
「邪悪な者たちに平和はない」
Or put another way,
ですから 自分の道徳基準に従って
生きる邪悪な人たちは
those who wickedly set
their own moral standards
will receive no peace from Jehovah
and will not have peaceful lives.
エホバから平和を与えられず
平和を味わうことはないのです
But we work hard
to live by Jehovah’s standards.
ぜひエホバの基準に従うように
努力し続けましょう
もちろんエホバは助けてくれますが
Now, it’s true
that Jehovah does his part to help us,
but he does expect us to do our part.
私たちが努力することを望んでいます
エホバはいわば掛け算のように
We could say that his blessing on our effort
私たちの努力を祝福してくださると
言えます どういうことでしょうか
is somewhat like multiplication.
What do we mean?
私たちの努力が0だと
エホバは祝福できません
Well, if we put forth no effort,
there’s nothing for Jehovah to multiply.
0×10は何ですか 0です
What is ten times zero?
Zero.
0×100 1000 10000だと
どうですか やはり0です
a hundred times zero?
a thousand times zero?
a million times zero?
We still have zero.
ですから 何も努力しないなら
エホバは祝福しようがないのです
So if we don’t do anything,
Jehovah has nothing to multiply.
Galatians 5:22 tells us that peace
ガラテア 5:22によると
平和は「聖なる力が
生み出すもの」の一面です
is an aspect
of “the fruitage of the [holy] spirit.”
ですから 平和をつくる人になれるよう
So the holy spirit will help us
cultivate and demonstrate peace.
聖なる力が助けてくれます
In fact, John 14:26
ヨハネ 14:26では
聖なる力が「援助者」と呼ばれています
describes the holy spirit as a “helper.”
But that expression “helper”
ですが 援助者がいるからといって
doesn’t indicate
it will miraculously do the job for us
私たちの側に何の努力も必要ない
ということではありません
with no effort on our part.
例えで考えてみましょう
To illustrate this if we can:
あなたが自分の家の外壁に
Imagine that you’re working very hard
一生懸命ペンキを塗っているとします
to paint the outside of your house,
and a good friend comes to help you.
そこへ友達がやって来て
塗るのを手伝ってくれます
Now you’re painting together.
でもあなたは 「自分はもう家に入って
ゆっくりしよう」と考えます
But then you decide,
‘I’ll just go back in the house,
and I’ll just take it easy.’
Well, how long
will your friend keep painting?
では 友達はどうするでしょうか
If he continued painting,
he’s no longer a helper;
ペンキを塗り続けたら
もう援助者ではなく
あなたの代わりに
働いていることになります
he’s doing the job for you.
ルカ 11:13には
Luke 11:13 tells us that Jehovah
エホバは「求めている人に
聖なる力を与えてくださる」とあります
will “give holy spirit
to those asking him” for it.
So if we ask for holy spirit
ですから 聖なる力を求めて
and then do our very best
to work in harmony with that helper,
その援助者に助けてもらいながら
努力するなら
神との平和な関係を楽しめます
we will enjoy peace with God
and we will enjoy and promote harmony,
そして 他の人とも争うことなく
仲の良い平和な関係を
持つことができるでしょう
unity, and good relations with others.
And what a pleasure it is
to associate with those who display peace
聖なる力が生み出すものの重要な一面で
ある平和を愛する人たちとの交友は
—this important aspect
of the spirit’s fruitage!
本当に素晴らしいものです
When a sleeping baby
眠っている赤ちゃんが夜中に
目を覚ましてしまうことがあります
is suddenly awakened
in the middle of the night by a loud noise,
大きな音がしたので
he becomes frightened
—doesn’t he?—
その音にびっくりして
泣き出してしまいます
and he cries out for help.
But when a parent cuddles him
でも 親が優しく抱き上げて
and soothes him with reassuring words,
安心させるように声を掛けてあやすと
落ち着きを取り戻します
he calms down immediately.
同じように
詩編 55:16-18にある通り
Well, David at Psalm 55:16-18
ダビデはつらい状況に直面して
said that when he was troubled,
he ‘called out to God’
「神に向かって叫」びました
すると エホバがその「声を聞いて」
and that Jehovah
‘heard his voice’ and ‘gave him peace.’
「安らぎを与えて」くれました
Like David, when we’re in anguish,
私たちもダビデのようにつらい時に
祈りで天の父に呼び掛けるなら
we can supplicate our heavenly Father,
エホバは落ち着かせてくださり
and he will soothe and restore our peace.
安らぎを与えてくださいます
In fact, our loving Father
is eager to do this for us.
実際 エホバはぜひとも
私たちを助けたいと思っています
Open up to Jeremiah chapter 29,
エレミヤ 29章を見ると
and notice that he’s eager
to replace our anxiety
エホバが私たちの不安を取り除いて
安らぎを与えたいと思っていることが
よく分かります
with the peace from him.
29:11, 12
Jeremiah 29:11:
“‘For I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you,’
「エホバはこう宣言する
『私は あなたたちのために自分が
行おうとしていることをよく知っている
“declares Jehovah,
“‘thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
あなたたちに災いではなく
平和をもたらし
“‘to give you a future and a hope.
良い将来と希望を与えたいと思っている
“‘And you will call me
and come and pray to me,
あなたたちが私を呼び
私のもとに来て祈る時
and I will listen to you.’”
私は耳を傾ける』」
Isn’t that beautiful?
素晴らしいですね エホバは喜んで
Our God is ready, willing, and able
to replace our anxieties
私たちの心配や不安を
取り除いてくださり
with this amazing peace
that only he can give.
ご自分にしか与えられない平和を
与えてくださるのです
ここまでで エホバが
平和の神であることを考えました
Well, we’ve now discussed
how Jehovah is the God of peace.
誰に平和を与えるかも考えました
We’ve discussed who he gives the peace to
—to those who draw close to him
神との絆を強めようと努力し
and earnestly seek peace from him.
平和を求める人たちです
では これから考えたいのは
But now let’s examine how each of us
私たちがどのように平和をつくる人に
なれるかという点です
can promote peace with others.
In the following video,
次のビデオの中で統治体の
ケニス・クック兄弟が
Brother Kenneth Cook of the Governing Body
will explain how this convention program
平和をつくる上で
この大会のプログラムが
どう役立つかということを
説明してくださいます
will help us to pursue peace.
On behalf of the Governing Body,
統治体を代表して
「平和をつくる」地区大会を
視聴している皆さんを
I can say that we really appreciate
your attending
this “Pursue Peace”! Convention.
心から歓迎します
Speaking of peace,
ところで 世界本部があるここ
ニューヨーク州ブルー湖は
we love the serene setting
here at our world headquarters
まさに心安らぐ場所です
on Blue Lake in New York State.
湖面が鏡のように
景色を映すこともあります
At times, the water is as smooth as a mirror.
We occasionally see eagles and hawks fly by.
ワシやタカが飛んでくることもあります
秋になると 山々は鮮やかに紅葉します
And in the fall of the year
when the leaves change color,
the forest can look spectacular.
素晴らしい景色です
でも もっと素晴らしいのは
More important
than this tranquil setting, though,
is the abundant peace
エホバがご自分の組織に
与えている豊かな平和です
that Jehovah has given to his organization.
We can say this because of the peace
and harmony that unite us
エホバが平和を与えてくださるので
私たちは国 言語 人種 部族
no matter what our nationality,
language, race, tribe,
or social background is.
社会的立場の壁を越えて
一致していられます
This is truly spectacular,
この平和は素晴らしいものです
especially when we consider
all the turmoil in the world
世界のどこでも分断が進み
人々が政治 宗教
and how divided people are
politically, socially, and religiously.
社会問題を巡って分かれているからです
However, we cannot take
our beautiful peace for granted;
でも この平和は
偶然に生じるものではなく
it’s not maintained automatically.
みんなでつくり上げるものです
Each of us personally must pursue peace
神に喜ばれるには一人一人が
平和をつくらなければなりません
in order to have God’s approval.
Jehovah certainly wants his worshippers
to enjoy lasting peace.
エホバは兄弟姉妹の平和を願っています
That was true in ancient times.
昔もそうでした
God told Moses to have the priests in Israel
イスラエルの祭司は
民のために祝福を願う際
bless the people with very reassuring words.
こう言うことになっていました
Notice these words that we find
その言葉を見てみましょう
at Numbers 6:24-26,
民数記 6:24-26です
and hear what the priests
were to say to the people:
祭司たちは こう言いました
“May Jehovah bless you and safeguard you.
「エホバがあなたを祝福して
守ってくださいますように
“May Jehovah make his face shine upon you,
エホバが笑顔をあなたに向け
恵みを与えてくださいますように
“and may he favor you.
“May Jehovah lift up his face toward you
エホバがあなたに向かって顔を上げ
平和を与えてくださいますように」
and grant you peace.”
27節 「彼らは
イスラエルの民のために
The next verse states:
“And they must place my name
私の名を言わなければならない
“upon the people of Israel,
私が民を祝福するためである」
that I may bless them.”
Jehovah has placed his name on us too,
私たちも神の名を大切にし
and he is richly blessing us.
祝福されています
Let’s consider what
this convention program is going to cover
この大会で学べる点を概観しましょう
so that we’ll know how we can continue
どうすればエホバから平和を
与えていただけるかを学べます
to enjoy God’s blessing of peace.
第一に 神との平和について考えます
First, we’ll consider
how to be at peace with God.
エホバとの絆があれば
Our greatest peace comes
from having
a personal relationship with Jehovah.
穏やかで平和な心を持てます
Making him our best Friend benefits us
エホバを一番の友達にするなら
and leads to peace
in every other aspect of our life.
どんな状況でも
平和を失うことはありません
How can we reach out
for a close relationship with God?
どうすればエホバと
親しくなれるのでしょうか
We need more
than a superficial knowledge of him.
頭だけの知識では不十分です
We need to get to know Jehovah as a person
エホバがどんな感情を持つ方かを知って
and admire his qualities and ways.
エホバを敬うことが必要です
Then we can love what he loves
エホバが愛するものを愛し
and hate what he hates.
憎むものを憎むのです
During this program,
この大会で真剣に学ぶなら
listen for details about Jehovah
エホバともっと親しくなれるでしょう
that will draw you ever closer to him.
第二に 周りの人との
平和について考えます
Second, we’ll consider
how to be at peace with others.
Our homes should be havens
for peace for our families.
家庭は安らぎの場であるべきです
This means more than the absence of arguing.
言い争わないのはもちろん
It involves putting the interests
of our family members ahead of our own.
自分のことより家族を
優先するということです
As we’ll learn from this program,
後で学びますが そのために必要なのは
that includes showing love
and respect to one another,
愛と敬意 みんなの協力
working as a team,
良いコミュニケーション
improving family communication,
and worshipping Jehovah together.
一緒にエホバに仕えることです
第三に 試練や大変な中での
平和について考えます
Third, we’ll consider
how to be at peace despite trials
and troublesome world conditions.
During this convention,
we’re going to tour the world to see how,
この大会では 世界各地の
兄弟たちの経験を聞けます
despite opposition, illness,
反対 病気 失業
economic problems, and natural disasters,
災害に立ち向かいながら
our brothers really care for one another,
互いを心から気遣い
how they receive help
from Jehovah’s organization,
エホバの組織から助けを与えられ
エホバに仕え続けているという経験です
and how they continue
their spiritual activity.
No matter what may threaten
our lives or livelihood,
命の危険や生活の不安があっても
we can be confident
that Jehovah can help us get through it
エホバは忍耐できるよう助け
心の平和を与えてくださいます
and retain our peace of mind and heart.
第四に 新しい世界での
平和について考えます
Fourth, we’ll consider
how to enjoy peace eternally.
神の王国の助けによって
人間が完全になったら
Once God’s Kingdom
has lifted mankind to perfection,
we’ll no longer have to pursue peace.
状況は大きく変わります
詩編 72:7の 「平和が行き渡る
As Psalm 72:7 promises:
“The righteous will flourish,
月がなくなる時までも」という
言葉の通りになります
and peace will abound
until the moon is no more.”
In other words, there will be peace forever.
つまり 平和が永遠に続きます
This program will help us
エホバは将来 素晴らしい祝福を
与えてくださるのです
to anticipate future blessings from Jehovah.
Can you see why “Pursue Peace!”
今年の大会のテーマは
平和をつくるというものです
was well chosen
as the theme for this year’s convention?
To pursue something means
平和をつくるには いろいろな面で
努力しなければなりません
to chase it in order to capture it.
Because of the influence of Satan,
サタンの影響 今の悪い世界
his wicked world, and our own imperfections,
受け継いだ不完全さのせいで
peace is constantly trying to elude us.
平和は壊れやすいものです
Therefore, we have to chase after it
to capture it in our lives.
平和を壊さないために
真剣な努力が必要です
This convention program will help us do that.
何ができるか みんなで学びましょう
平和の神が いつも皆さんと
共にいてくださいますように
May the God of peace
be with all of you now and forever!
That’s the heartfelt wish
of all of us on the Governing Body
統治体全員は心からそう願っています
皆さんを深く愛しているからです
because we love you dearly.
Please enjoy the entire convention program!
ぜひこの大会をお楽しみください
クック兄弟 ありがとうございました
We warmly thank Brother Cook
for highlighting
some of the ways
this convention program
平和をつくるのにこの大会の
プログラムがどのように役立つか
will help us to pursue peace.
教えていただきました
But now let’s briefly preview
では 平和の神が私たちのために
準備してくださった
the convention program that is coming our way
この大会のプログラム全体を
ご一緒に少し概観してみましょう
that has been provided by the God of peace,
and you may want to follow along
by using your copy
よろしければお手元のプログラムを見て
内容に注目してください
of the convention program.
You’ll note that day one has the theme
1日目の主題は 「エホバはその民に
平和を与えて祝福する」というものです
“Jehovah will bless his people with peace.”
最初のシンポジウムでは
The first symposium will illustrate
神を愛し 隣人を愛し
聖書を愛するなら
how love for God, love for neighbor,
and love for God’s Word
本当の平和を味わえる
ということについて学べます
lead to genuine peace.
今年の劇形式の聖書朗読では
This year’s dramatic Bible reading
is based on the life of Jacob.
ヤコブについて取り上げられます
And as you will see,
Jacob gives us an excellent example
ヤコブが「平和に役立つこと⋯⋯を
何でも行［う］」という点で
as to how we can
“pursue the things
私たちにとってどのように素晴らしい
手本となっているか学びましょう
making for peace.”
その後
Thereafter, we’ll have the talk
「真の正しさは平和をもたら［す］」
という話を聞くことができます
“The Result of True Righteousness
Will Be Peace,”
and we’ll see in that talk
how we can resist temptation.
どうすれば周りからの圧力に
抵抗できるかが取り上げられます
Just as a lion devours prey
and assimilates it into his body,
ライオンが食べたものが
ライオンの体の一部になるように
サタンは私たちに圧力をかける
ことによってむさぼり食おうとし
Satan tries to get us
to succumb to temptations
so that he can devour us
and assimilate us into his world.
自分の世の一部に
ならせようとしています
But during that talk,
we’ll learn how to reject his temptations.
ぜひサタンからの圧力に
抵抗する方法を学びましょう
Then in the second half of day one,
1日目の午後の部では まずこの大会の
2つ目のシンポジウムがあります
we’ll enjoy our second convention symposium,
“Take Delight in God’s Promises of Peace.”
「神は平和をつくってくださる！」
という主題です
We will be greatly heartened
by Jehovah’s promises of peace
イザヤ書に書かれている
平和についてのエホバの約束に
力づけられるでしょう
found in the book of Isaiah.
For example, one of the talks has the theme
例えば 1つの話の題は
“The Wolf and the Lamb Will Feed Together.”
「オオカミと子羊が
一緒に食べ［る］」というものです
Today, we can’t even imagine
feeding a wolf and a lamb together.
現在では これはなかなか
想像しにくいことですね
一緒に食べさせようとしても
If we tried such, it would likely result
おそらく子羊がオオカミのディナーに
なってしまうことでしょう
in lamb chops for the wolf.
でもイザヤ書の中で
エホバが約束している通り
But Jehovah’s promise in Isaiah assures us
将来 動物同士が
平和に暮らすようになり
that peace will exist
between humans and animals
and between animals and other animals.
人間と動物も平和な関係になります
The third convention symposium
has a thought-provoking theme
この大会の3つ目のシンポジウムの
テーマも興味深いものです
“Follow the Road Map to Family Peace.”
「家庭の平和に欠かせないもの」
というものです
We’ll learn how, despite challenges,
夫婦や親や子供たちが
marriage mates, parents, and children
いろいろな課題を乗り越えながら
どのように家庭の平和に貢献できるかを
学ぶことができます
can successfully follow
that road map to family peace.
Then we’ll enjoy the talk
次の話は 「『平和の統治者』を
心から支持する」という題です
“Loyally Support the ‘Prince of Peace.’”
That talk will remind us
この話を通して 政治的な問題で
中立を保つことの大切さを
of the importance
of maintaining our neutrality
by not taking sides on political issues.
思い起こすことができます
1日目の最後の話の主題は何でしょうか
To conclude day one,
we’ll have the intriguing talk
“Do Not Be Misled by Imitation Peace!”
「偽物の平和に
惑わされないでください」です
It will contrast the world’s so-called peace
世の中で考えられている平和と
イエスが弟子たちに与える
本物の平和との違いが論じられます
with a genuine peace
that Jesus will give his followers.
But then on day two,
では 2日目の主題は何でしょうか
notice the theme
「汚点も傷もない平和な人と
神に認めていただ［く］」です
“Be found . . . spotless
and unblemished and in peace.”
The second day starts with a symposium
最初にシンポジウムを通して
伝道を行い続けるための
励みを得ることができます
designed to invigorate us for our ministry
so that we can be ready
平和の良い知らせを伝えるために
to share the good news of peace.
どんな努力を払えるか学びましょう
That will be followed by the talk
次の話の主題は
「若い皆さん 平和につながる
進路を選んでください」です
“Young People
—Choose a Path That Leads to Peace!”
And that talk will encourage
our dear young ones
若い方々に全時間奉仕を
行うよう励ます話です
to pursue the full-time ministry.
And we want to say to you dear young ones
若い皆さんが全時間奉仕を行うなら
that if you do this,
you will enjoy a happy life
素晴らしい人生を送ることができ
決して後悔はしません
and you will have no regrets.
次に動画を見ます
Next, we will see a video
that shows how our brothers around the world
世界各地の兄弟姉妹が
are continuing their spiritual activity
さまざまな問題に直面しながらも
平和な心を持ってエホバに仕えている
様子を見ることができます
and are enjoying peace
despite difficult trials.
Then a highlight of the day
次は イエスの新しい弟子たちが
will be the baptism
of new disciples of Jesus.
いよいよバプテスマを受ける時です
In the baptism talk, the baptism candidates
話の中で バプテスマ希望者たちは
次のように勧められます
will be encouraged
to “Go On Walking ‘in the Way of Peace.’”
「『平和の道』」を
進み続けてください」
And why?
なぜそうすべきかというと
Because this is truly the best way of life.
それがまさに最高の生き方だからです
午後の部の2つのシンポジウムでは
Two more symposiums
will use video dramatizations
一連のビデオを通して学び
to contrast traits of peace wreckers
平和を壊す人と平和をつくる人の違いを
理解することができます
with the qualities of peacemakers.
その二者には本当に大きな違いが
あることがはっきり分かるでしょう
And what a stark contrast between the two
you’ll see in these symposiums!
It’s kind of like the contrast
between bitter and sweet.
しょっぱい塩と甘い砂糖ぐらい
全然違います
Part 1 of this year’s Bible drama
聖書に基づく今年のドラマの第1部では
will remind us of ancient examples
of God’s people who pursued peace,
エホバに仕えて平和をつくった
昔の人たちについて思い起こします
and we’ll definitely be able
to relate to their examples
その人たちの手本を今の私たちの生活に
どのように当てはめられるかを考えます
and relate it
to our current situation in life.
The day will conclude with showing us
2日目の最後の話では
「『平和という絆』を守る」方法に
ついて取り上げられます
how to “Safeguard
Our ‘Uniting Bond of Peace’!”
We’ll see how we can do so
それを守るには 国や地方の
文化や伝統に従うことよりも
by putting the application
of Bible principles
always ahead
of following local culture and traditions.
聖書の原則に沿って
行動することの方が大切です
3日目の主題は
「希望を与える神が⋯⋯
Now on day three, the theme is
“May the God who gives hope
皆さんをあらゆる喜びと平和で
満たしてくださ［る］」です
fill you with all joy and peace.”
午前のシンポジウムでは
全部で7つの例を考えます
The opening symposium
will examine seven examples
of ones who sowed peace and reaped peace.
「平和の種をまいて平和を
刈り取った人たち」の例です
We will examine Joseph and his brothers,
取り上げられるのは ヨセフと兄たち
ギベオンの人たち ギデオン
the Gibeonites, Gideon, Abigail,
アビガイル メピボセテ
パウロとバルナバ
Mephibosheth, Paul and Barnabas,
and modern examples.
そして現代の例です
続く公開聖書講演を
We truly hope that many accept our invitation
to hear the enlightening
ぜひとも大勢の方々に
聞いていただきたいと思っています
public Bible discourse
entitled “Friendship With God
—How Possible?”
講演の主題は
「神と友達になるには」というものです
Now, if we think about it,
私たちはアダムの子孫で罪深いので
we’re not born as friends of God
because we’re born
as sinful offspring of Adam.
生まれつき神の友達ではありません
Actually, if you think about it,
生まれた時は神の敵のような状態です
we’re born as enemies of God.
Sometimes you’ll hear
people say of a little baby,
ある人は赤ちゃんを見てこう言います
「かわいいわね 天使みたい」
“Look at that little angel,”
but more accurate would be to say,
でも正しくはこうですね
“Look at that little enemy of God.”
「かわいいわね 神の敵だけど」
Now, of course, we love that little baby.
もちろん そのかわいい赤ちゃんには
希望があります
And it’s not hopeless
because our loving Creator
神は その赤ちゃんを含め 全ての人が
has made reconciliation with him
ご自分と和解できるように
してくださったからです
within the reach of everyone.
We can become a good friend of God.
皆が神の友達になれます
そして エホバとの友情関係は
And that close relationship with Jehovah
will become our most valuable possession.
私たちにとって最も大切なものです
But then after we enjoy
Part 2 of the Bible drama,
ドラマの第2部を楽しんだ後
この大会の結びの話を
聞くことができます
the concluding talk of this convention
will fill our hearts with a joyful prospect
「誰もがエホバに仕え
平和になる時が来る！」と題する話で
that “Universal Peace Is Sure to Come!”
喜びに満ちた将来について考えます
It’s guaranteed by the God “who cannot lie.”
「偽ることができ［ない］」神が
約束しているものです
最後に新しいオリジナルソングを
一緒に歌い
Finally, we’ll join in singing
a beautiful new original song
平和の源であるエホバに
賛美の祈りを捧げて
and we’ll close with a prayer of praise
to Jehovah,
the Source of peace.
大会を終えたいと思います
So, dear brothers and sisters,
兄弟姉妹の皆さん
there’s a brief synopsis
3日間のプログラムがますます
楽しみになったでしょうか
of our wonderful three-day convention
平和の神が用意してくださった
この大会を
provided by the God of peace
that is coming our way.
ぜひ漏らさず視聴しましょう
And throughout,
プログラム全体を通して
the program will be enhanced
with dozens of videos,
興味深いたくさんのビデオも出てきます
and we’ll see our brothers
either in real-life settings
兄弟姉妹たちの経験談やインタビュー
またドラマ仕立てのビデオなどがあって
or dramatizations
that we’ll definitely be able to relate to.
共感したり教訓を学んだり
できるでしょう
In fact, the following video
ここでもビデオを見てみましょう
is a little, or small, sampling of the videos
この大会で見るいろいろな
ビデオのダイジェストを
you will see during this convention.
少しお見せしたいと思います
Hey, everyone.
ねえみんな 誰だと思う？
オリビアです
Guess who just walked in?
Olivia.
今日も投票よろしく
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
しないでしょ 超真面目だもん
I wanted to go up to the girls
and smash their phones.
あの子たちのところに行って
携帯壊したかった
Neutral?
Ain’t no neutral.
中立？ そんなのないんだよ！
臆病者！
You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
こんなもん ごみだ
What I was feeling back then
ニューヨークにいた頃は悲しくて
全然平和な気持ちではありませんでした
was just sadness,
never really peace.
皆さんこんにちは
デミュアデザインのヘイリーです
Hello, everyone.
Haley from DeNure Design here.
Is there just a little bit of envy in there?
ちょっとねたんでるところない？
2018年6月
In June of 2018,
a huge group of armed men came to us.
武装した集団が
うちに押し掛けてきました
They represented the ideals of my childhood.
警察官は子供の頃の私の憧れでした
Do you have any idea
what this is going to cost us?
これ どれだけコストかかるか
分かってんのか？
しょうがないだろ
こっちは聞いてなかったんだから
I didn’t have a choice.
You went behind my back!
マスクは？
Where’s your mask?
Do you know how many people
have actually gotten sick?
会社で何人感染したか知ってる？
Zero.
ゼロだよ
That’s what always happens.
こういうことはよくあります
もう駄目だと思った時
When you’re just
about to lose all your strength,
エホバは私たちを元気づけるために
必ず何かをしてくれるんです
Jehovah does that something for you.
平和な関係を取り戻せて本当に良かった
I’m so grateful that we made peace
before the world turned upside down.
世界が大変なことになる前に
では 次の重要な点を考えましょう
But here’s an important question
for all of us:
この大会で神から平和を
与えていただくために
Will we prepare our heart
to receive God’s peace
during this convention?
私たちは心を整えるでしょうか
Ezra 7:10 tells us
エズラ 7:10にはこうあります
「エズラは エホバの律法を
調べて実践するため
that ‘Ezra prepared his heart
to consult the Law of Jehovah
また⋯⋯イスラエルで教えるため
心を整えていた」
and to practice it,
and to teach it to the Israelites.’
Now, what was the result?
その結果 11節にあるようにエズラは
Verse 11 tells us
he became “an expert in the study
「エホバのおきて⋯⋯の研究者」として
熱心に奉仕できました
of the commandments of Jehovah.”
Well, in imitation of Ezra,
では エズラに倣って
how can we prepare our heart
この大会で学ぶために
どのように心を整えることが
できるでしょうか
for what we’re going to take in
at this convention?
Well, for one thing (very important),
by prayer and meditation,
とても大切なのは 祈りと黙想です
we can make sure that our heart is ready,
その2つを行って 自分の心が
エホバからの教育を受け入れる用意が
できているようにしましょう
receptive to receive Jehovah’s instruction.
そして心の中で
And we can also make sure that in our heart,
エホバが教えてくださることを
当てはめる決意をするようにしましょう
we are determined
to apply what Jehovah teaches us.
But then another thing we can do
さらにできるのは
大会中に毎日流される
is we can pay close attention
ミュージックビデオを
注意深く見ることです
to the music-video presentations
that will be shown before every session
as the convention begins.
3日間の午前の部と
午後の部の最初に流されます
Now, these presentations
have been carefully crafted
どのミュージックビデオも
入念に準備されていて
私たちが心を整えるのに
とても役立ちます
to help prepare our heart for each session.
Much time, effort, and expense
たくさんの美しいミュージックビデオを
制作するために
has been expended in preparing
多くの時間や労力や
費用がかけられました
these beautiful presentations.
So please listen carefully
as the sounds and scenes
ぜひじっくり耳を傾けてください
音楽や映像によって心が整えられ
prepare your heart to accept
the spiritual instruction
その後に学ぶ事柄を受け入れる
用意ができるでしょう
that will follow.
Yes, may each of us be determined
私たち一人一人が この大会で
エホバが教えてくださることに
to listen attentively
十分に注意を払うことができますように
to what Jehovah is teaching us.
May we be determined to imitate the psalmist
詩編 85:8で次のように述べた
詩編作者の謙遜な態度に
ぜひ倣いましょう
who humbly stated at Psalm 85:8:
“I will listen
to what the true God Jehovah says,
「私は真の神エホバが語ることを聞く
for he will speak peace to his people.”
神は民に⋯⋯平和を語る」
If we do, we will learn
how to pursue peace with all people
注意深く聞くなら どうすれば
平和をつくれるかが分かります
to the praise of Jehovah, the God of peace,
そして 平和を与えてくださる
平和の神エホバを賛美できます
who blesses his people with peace.
Yes, we will be successful in pursuing peace
そうです 今平和をつくることが
できるようになり
将来は平和を追い求めなくてよいのです
until we no longer have to pursue it.
Now, what do we mean?
Well, think about it.
エホバについて考えてみましょう
Does Jehovah have to pursue peace?
エホバは平和を追い求めますか
Does he have to chase it
in an effort to try to catch it?
いわば平和を捕まえようとしますか
No.
いいえ エホバは平和を表すのです
Jehovah merely displays peace.
Well, in the new world,
新しい世界では素晴らしいことに
what a wonderful time it will be
私たちも平和を追い求める
必要はなくなります
when we no longer have to pursue peace,
but like Jehovah,
we can merely display peace.
エホバのように平和を表すことに
専念できるのです
でも今は ぜひ平和を追い求めることを
決意しましょう
But right now, let’s be determined
to continue to pursue peace.
この素晴らしい大会が
And may this wonderful convention
私たちが平和をつくる上で
that is coming our way help us to do so!
大きな助けになりますように！
レット兄弟 ありがとうございました
Thank you, Brother Lett, for helping us
prepare our hearts
心を整えるように助けられました
for the rest of the program.
We are ready for Jehovah to teach us
how to pursue peace.
平和をつくるにはどうしたらよいかを
学ぶ用意ができました
次に考えることができるのは
How is peace related to love?
平和と愛の関係です
How can we show love?
And what blessings result when we do?
愛を表すとどうなるのでしょうか
この大会の最初のシンポジウムから
ご一緒に学びましょう
The first symposium of this convention
will answer those questions.
Brother Seth Hyatt,
統治体の奉仕委員会の援助者
セス・ハイアット兄弟が
a helper to the Service Committee
of the Governing Body,
1つ目の話をしてくださいます
will begin with the talk
主題は 「愛があれば平和になる
神を愛する」です
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love for God.”
どう思いますか
What do you think?
Is there a connection, a relationship,
愛と平和の間には
何か関係があるでしょうか
between love and peace?
もしあるなら 平和を得る上で
And if so, what role does love play
愛はどんな役割を果たしますか
in achieving genuine peace?
聖書が述べるところによれば
The Bible helps us to appreciate
that love is an essential element
愛は平和を得るのに欠かせません
それは本当に大切です
in achieving genuine peace.
それで私たちは愛を示すようにします
So we’re interested in showing love.
聖書を学んで知っているように
As students of the Bible, we know
人間は神に似た者として造られました
that humans were created
in the image of God.
And as a result,
you and I have the ability to show love.
私たちが愛を示すことが
できるのはそのためです
でもご存じのように
But we also know that we live in a world
私たちが住んでいる世界には
that has a very distorted view
愛についてゆがんだ見方が見られます
and definition of love.
That, combined with our own imperfection,
それに私たちは不完全です
それで注意しないと
means that if we’re not careful,
our view of love can become distorted.
私たちの見方もゆがんでしまいます
どうすればそれを避けられますか
So how do we guard against that?
愛し方をエホバに教えて
いただくことによってです
By allowing Jehovah to teach us how to love.
その点でエホバ以上の方はいません
And when you think about it,
what better teacher could we have?
The Bible says that “God is love.”
聖書によれば 「神は愛」です
エホバは創造者で 私たちのことを
That means that Jehovah, our Creator
—who knows us better than we know ourselves,
私たち以上によく知っています
そして 行うこと全てに
愛があふれています
who embodies, who personifies love—
is willing to teach us how to love.
その方が愛について
教えてくださるのです
どのようにですか
And how does he do that?
Well, by means of his Word, the Bible,
ご自分の言葉 聖書によって
and by means of his own beautiful example.
またご自分の素晴らしい
手本によってです
As we get acquainted with Jehovah,
エホバを知るにつれて
本当の愛とは何かが分かってきます
we learn what love really is.
And as we put that love to work,
そして 愛を行動で表す点で
イエスに倣えます
as Jesus did,
then we’re in a position
私たちがそうするなら
to enjoy genuine peace.
本当の平和を味わえます
このシンポジウムで
In this symposium,
we’re going to explore how love for God,
愛があれば平和になることを学びます
love of neighbor,
神への愛 隣人への愛 聖書への愛が
and love for God’s Word, the Bible,
can lead to genuine peace.
どのように平和につながるかです
まず神への愛を考えます
First, let’s talk about love for God.
How important is that
平和を味わうために
愛はどれほど大切ですか
if we want to enjoy genuine peace?
イエスがマタイ 22章で
述べた言葉から
Well, Jesus provides some insight
in a statement he made
that’s recorded in our Bibles
at Matthew chapter 22.
その答えを知るヒントが
得られるので 見てみましょう
Let’s look at it.
Matthew chapter 22,
マタイ 22:37を読みましょう
and we’re going to read verse 37.
まず文脈を見てみると
Now, to provide some context for these words,
この時イエスは律法に通じた
男性からこう質問されました
Jesus has been asked a question by a man
who is well-versed in the Law.
「律法の中で最も重要な
おきてはどれですか」
“[What] is the greatest commandment
in the Law?”
Notice how Jesus responds:
答えに注目しましょう
「イエスは言った
“He said to him:
『「あなたは 心を尽くし
知力を尽くし
“‘You must love Jehovah your God
“‘with your whole heart
自分の全てを尽くして
“‘and with your whole soul
あなたの神エホバを
愛さなければならない」
“and with your whole mind.’
これが最も重要な第一のおきてです』」
This is the greatest and first commandment.”
「あなたの神エホバを
愛さなければならない」
“You must love Jehovah your God”
—a command.
命令です
エホバを愛することはとても重要で
Love for Jehovah is essential.
It has to be
the most important relationship in our life.
それは生活の中で最も大切な関係です
More important than any human,
どんな人間との関係よりも
more important than any thing
どんなものよりも大切です
—we want to love Jehovah.
エホバを愛したいと思いますが
どれほどですか
To what extent?
Well, Jesus says: “with your whole heart.”
イエスは「心を尽くし」と言いました
What does that involve?
どういうことでしょうか
続く言葉と合わせて考えると
The context of Jesus’ words
イエスが使った「心」
という言葉はここで
helps us to understand that he was talking
about a person’s feelings,
人の気持ち 感情 欲求を指しています
emotions, desires.
神への愛に感情が
関係するということですか
So does love for God involve our emotions?
その通りです
Absolutely!
でも神への単なる愛情以上のものが
関係しています
But it has to involve more
than a simple affection for God.
Why do we say that?
なぜそう言えますか
聖句を見ましょう
Well, what did Jesus say next?
イエスはここで「自分の全てを
尽くして」とも言っています
“With your whole soul,”
that is, with your entire being.
We use everything we have
それで持っているもの全てを使って
to praise Jehovah
エホバを賛美し 神への愛を表します
and to prove our love for him.
もう1つあります
But even more is involved.
Jesus concludes by saying:
「知力を尽くし」とも
イエスは言っています
“with your whole mind.”
So our intellectual faculties are involved.
私たちの思考力が関係しています
私たちは時間を取って
We’re willing to take the time
エホバのお考えを知るようにし
to get to know Jehovah’s thinking
それに自分の考えを合わせます
and make it our thinking.
We want to think the way Jehovah thinks.
エホバと同じように考えたいと思います
We want to understand his purpose
エホバがどんな方で
私たちにどんなことを求めておられるか
and his requirements for us,
そしてエホバの目的を
理解したいと思います
and we want to understand his personality.
このような愛について考えてくると
Now, when we think about that kind of love,
it’s clear that it encompasses
それに何が含まれるかは明らかです
our thoughts, our words, and our actions.
考え 言葉 行動 全てが含まれます
Nothing is left out.
And that kind of love
このような愛によって
私たちは神との友情を
持つことができます
provides a basis for a friendship with God.
And that results in peace with God.
それは神との平和をもたらします
So there we see the progression.
つながりが見えてきましたね
心と知力と自分の全てを尽くして
Loving Jehovah with our whole heart,
soul, and mind
エホバを愛するなら
神との平和が得られます
leads to peace with God.
そして 神との平和があれば
And as we enjoy peace with God,
we can also enjoy inner peace
心の平和と
and peace with those around us.
周りの人たちとの平和も味わえます
Now, how does that work?
どうしてですか
エホバを愛するとエホバに
倣いたいと感じます
Well, our love for Jehovah
motivates us to imitate him,
and we cultivate the qualities
エホバが持っている性質を身に付け
示すよう努力します
that Jehovah displays,
for example: patience,
例えば 辛抱 親切 温和です
kindness, mildness
そうした性質はほかの人を引き付け
—qualities that make us attractive to others,
and qualities that promote peace with others.
ほかの人との平和を築くのに役立ちます
皆さんも神と平和な関係で
いたいと思われるでしょう
I’m sure you would agree
that we want to be at peace with God.
But sometimes our peace can be threatened.
でも平和が奪われそうに
なる時もあります
ストレスを感じることもあれば
We may experience pressure.
ひどい扱いや不公正な扱いを受けたり
We may be the subject of some wrong,
悪いことをされたりすることも
あるかもしれません
some injustice, some evil
そんな時 平和が奪われかねません
that threatens our peace.
それで考えるべきなのは
And then the question is this:
エホバに喜ばれる仕方で
その状況に対処するか
Will we handle things in a way
that is pleasing to Jehovah
or will we become impatient
それとも自分のやり方で何とか
するしかないと思ってしまうかです
or try to take matters into our own hands?
In the following dramatization,
では次のビデオで ある家族が
notice how a family draws strength
from a Bible account
エホバの主権に対する愛と敬意を
思い出させる聖書の記述から
that highlights love and respect
力を得る様子を見てみましょう
for Jehovah’s sovereignty.
Olivia!
オリビア！ オリビア！
早く！ 学校に遅れるわよ
Hurry, you’re going to be late for school!
Thank you.
ありがとう
奉仕行ってくる
OK, Mom. I’m going to preach.
行ってきます じゃあね お母さん
See you.
Love you.
Bye, Mom. Love you.
はい 頑張ってね
Have a good day.
See you later, Mom.
行ってきます
今日も投票よろしく
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
She would never; she’s an angel.
しないでしょ 超真面目だもん
I think it’s all a front.
真面目ぶってるだけだって
ほんとはすごいんだから
You know she’s wild.
だよね
Oh, yeah.
Oh, she totally just saw us.
わあ なんかすごいこっち見てる！
OK. I’m totally posting that.
よし じゃあ これで上げちゃおう
Do it.
オッケー できた
OK. It’s up.
ねえみんな⋯⋯
Hey, everyone . . .
Did you just get that?
来た？
うん
Yeah.
すげえな
ねえみんな⋯⋯
Look at that.
Hey, everyone . . .
まじ受ける
That’s the craziest.
Oh, my goodness.
うわー
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
ねえみんな ブルックだよ
And Amanda.
アマンダです
Guess who just walked in?
来た来た 誰だと思う？
Olivia.
オリビアです
And there’s Jake.
で ジェイク
今日も投票よろしく
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
しないでしょ 超真面目だもん
I think it’s all an act.
真面目ぶってるだけだって
ほんとはすごいんだから
You know she’s wild.
あ こっち見るかな？あ 見た！
Oops, she saw us.
She saw us.
I don’t believe it.
超受けるんだけど なんて書く？
What are you going to comment?
I have no idea.
さあね
I don’t even think she likes guys.
男子に興味あんの？
What if she’s into girls?
レズなんじゃない？
That’s true. Yeah.
ほんとだ
そうだね
みんな書いてくれてる！
Comments!
Everybody is getting it.
みんな見たんだ！
I bet she’s still a virgin.
まだ未経験なんじゃないの？
Hey, can I see that?
ちょっと 見てもいい？
Yeah, of course.
あ もちろん
Here you go.
どうぞ
「いつまでも幸せに暮らせます」
へえ どうやって？
Enjoy Life Forever!
Now, how are you going to do that?
Well, that’s a very good question, actually.
そうですよね 実は神様が⋯⋯
Well, God promises . . .
No, no, no, not God, you!
いや いや いや いや いや
神じゃなくて あんただよ
What are you doing?
あんたは何やってんの？
Me? Well, I try to help others . . .
私？ あ 人を助けようと⋯⋯
Try?
助ける？ そこに突っ立ってる
だけじゃないか
Man, all you do
is stand next to your little cart
while the rest of us
stand up for your rights, bro.
こっちは自分たちの権利のために
もっとやってるんだ！
あ 私は中立を⋯⋯
Well, I’m actually neutral when it . . .
中立？ そんなのないんだよ！
臆病者！
Neutral?
Ain’t no neutral. You’re just a coward.
Take your trash.
こんなもん ごみだ
どうだった？
How did it go?
カートの奉仕 大変だった
でも大丈夫
It was a tough day at the cart, but I’m OK.
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
ねえみんな ブルックだよ
アマンダです
And Amanda.
Guess who just walked in?
来た来た 誰だと思う？
オリビア・・・
Olivia.
オリビア
Olivia,
what’s wrong?
何かあったの？
Hey, everyone, Brooke here.
ねえみんな ブルックだよ
And Amanda.
アマンダです
Guess who just walked in?
来た来た 誰だと思う？
Olivia.
オリビアです
で ジェイク
And there’s Jake.
今日も投票よろしく
Today’s poll: Would she ever?
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
No, she would never; she’s an angel.
しないでしょ 超真面目だもん
I think it’s all an act.
真面目ぶってるだけだって
ほんとはすごいんだから
You know she’s wild.
あ こっち見るかな？ あ 見た！
Oops, she saw us.
うーん 大変だったね
I’m so sorry that happened to you.
You know,
あのね
パウロが経験したことを思い出したの
it reminds me of a situation Paul was in.
確か 「使徒の活動」の
I think it was at Acts chapter 16
16章
and verse 23:
23節
“After they had inflicted many blows on them,
「そして 何度も打った後
“they threw them into prison
2人を牢屋に入れ
牢番に厳重に見張っておくよう命じた
“and ordered the jailer
to guard them securely.
“Because he got such an order, he threw them
そのような命令を受けたので
牢番は2人を奥の牢屋に入れ
“into the inner prison
“and fastened their feet in the stocks.
足かせをはめた
“But about the middle of the night,
しかし 真夜中ごろ
パウロとシラスは祈ったり
“Paul and Silas were praying
“and praising God with song,
歌で神を賛美したりしていて
and the prisoners were listening to them.”
囚人たちはそれを聞いていた」
What do you think made them want to sing?
なんで歌おうと思ったんだと思う？
エホバを愛していたのよね
They loved Jehovah.
そのことを考えて
どんな気持ちになったと思う？
And when they focused on that,
how do you think they felt?
I think
平和？
穏やかな気持ちかな？
they felt some peace.
That’s right.
そうね
How about we dig a little bit deeper?
もうちょっとみんなで
続きを見てみようか
いいよ
OK.
うん
Well, what did you notice?
どうでしたか
子供たち2人とも大変そうでしたね
Gabe and Olivia are under pressure
—Olivia in the classroom,
Gabe at the witnessing cart.
オリビアは学校で
ガブリエルは伝道でです
どのように対処すれば
How will they handle the pressure
この状況でエホバとの平和を保てますか
in a way that preserves
their peace with Jehovah?
大切な点です
Well, it’s a good question.
And really, all of us
大変な状況になる時
need to reflect on that question
私たち皆がこの点を
考える必要があります
when we’re under pressure.
私たちはエホバの方法が
最善であることも
We know that Jehovah’s way is the best way.
We’re convinced that his way of ruling
is the best way.
エホバの統治が最善であることも
よく分かっています
でも難しい状況に置かれると
But when we’re subjected to pressure,
例えば 不公正な扱いや
ひどい扱いを受けたり
perhaps the victim of some injustice
悪いことをされたりすると
or even of some evil,
自分のやり方で何とかするしかない
と思うかもしれません
we may be inclined
to take matters into our own hands.
でも そうすると平和を失いかねません
And when we do,
it can jeopardize our peace.
So how do we demonstrate respect
ではエホバの主権に対する敬意を
どのように表しますか
for Jehovah’s sovereignty?
The inspired advice
in Romans chapter 12 can help.
ローマ 12章にある
アドバイスが役立ちます
Let’s look together at Romans chapter 12,
見てみましょう
ローマ 12章の17節からです
beginning in verse 17:
“Return evil for evil to no one.”
「悪いことをされても」
と書かれています
そんな時にどうしたらよいと
述べられているでしょうか
So this provides the context
for what follows.
We may suffer some evil.
「悪いことをされても 決して
仕返しをしてはなりません
“Return evil for evil to no one.
どうすれば誰の目から見ても
良いことを行えるかを考えてください
Take into consideration what is fine
from the viewpoint of all men.”
できる限りのことをして
And then notice verse 18:
“If possible, as far as it depends
どんな人とも平和な関係で
いるようにしましょう」
“on you,
be peaceable (be a peacemaker)
with all men.”
つまり 平和をつくり出す
ということです
この言葉から エホバが無理な
要求をされないことが分かり
Now, these words
really heighten our appreciation
for Jehovah’s reasonableness.
本当に感謝が深まります
なぜそう言えますか
Why do we say that?
エホバは私たちに
Because Jehovah doesn’t ask us
to do something that we can’t do.
できないことをするよう
求めてはいないからです
平和をつくるためにエホバが
求めているのは何ですか
He doesn’t ask us to control others.
No,
できないことではなく
to the extent “it depends on you.”
「できる限りのこと」とあります
Jehovah asks that each of us
ほかの人はコントロールできませんが
control ourselves,
自分自身 自分の反応は
コントロールできます
our response to a situation,
エホバはそれを求めておられます
and to be peacemakers.
続く19節にこうあります
And then an explanation, verse 19:
“Do not avenge yourselves, beloved,
「愛する皆さん 復讐してはなりません
神の憤りに任せましょう」
なぜですか
but yield place to the wrath.”
Why?
“For it is written: ‘Vengeance is mine;
「『「復讐は私がすることであり
私が報復する」とエホバは言う』
と書いてあるからです」
I will repay,’ says Jehovah.”
So the advice is this:
まとめるとこうです
平和をつくり 神の憤りに任せましょう
Be a peacemaker,
and leave wrath to God.
Let him determine
if and when and upon whom
復讐するかどうか
いつ誰に復讐するかは
神に決めていただくのです
vengeance will be brought.
言うのは簡単です
It’s easy to say,
でもそうするのはいつでも簡単ですか
but is it always easy to do?
No.
いいえ
The example of King David
ダビデ王の手本は
この点でとても役立ちます
can be very helpful to us.
Through no fault of his own,
何も悪くなかったのに
David became the target
ダビデはサウル王に憎まれ
of King Saul’s murderous hatred.
命を狙われるようになりました
そしてサウルは何度も
ダビデを殺そうとします
And on several occasions,
Saul tried to kill David.
ダビデは何年も逃亡生活を送り
For several years David lived as a fugitive.
But there were opportunities during that time
その間に機会が開かれても
for David to harm Saul, even to kill him.
サウルに手を出し
殺すことはありませんでした
そうしたとしても正当化できたでしょう
He could have justified that in his mind.
But do you think had he done so
でも もしサウルを殺していたら
it would have threatened his peace
平和を 特にエホバとの平和を
失うことになったと思いませんか
—his peace, especially, with Jehovah?
そうです では ダビデは
どうしましたか
We know that it would.
So how did David respond?
ある時 部下たちに言いました
On one occasion, he said to his men:
“It is unthinkable from Jehovah’s standpoint
「私の主人に エホバが選んだ人に⋯⋯
このようなことをするなど
“that I should do such a thing to my lord,
エホバの観点からは
考えられないことです」
the anointed of Jehovah.”
何が分かりますか
What helped David?
Well, he saw a bigger picture
ダビデは自分とサウルの関係
以上のものを見ていました
than David and Saul, didn’t he?
エホバがどうご覧になるかを考えました
He saw a picture with David, Saul,
and Jehovah.
サウルが正されるべきなら
He knew that if Saul needed to be corrected,
エホバがご自分の時にご自分の方法で
そうされると分かっていました
Jehovah would do it in his time and way.
As a result, David was willing to be patient
それでダビデは辛抱し
and he preserved his peace
平和を保つことができました
神との平和 心の平和
周りの人たちとの平和です
—his peace with God, his inner peace,
and his peace with those around him.
素晴らしい手本です
What a beautiful example!
We can be sure that if we demonstrate
私たちもエホバの主権に
敬意を払うことにより
our love for Jehovah
エホバを待つことにより
エホバへの愛を表すなら
by respecting his sovereignty
and waiting on him,
we will enjoy peace as well.
平和を味わえると確信できます
エホバはご自分の民を祝福し
Jehovah assures us
that he will bless his people
平和を与えると
約束してくださっています
and he will bless us with peace.
では 心と知力と自分の
全てを尽くしてエホバを愛し
So let us be determined to love Jehovah
with our whole heart, soul, and mind
またエホバを待ち エホバの主権
物事の行い方に敬意を払うことにより
and to demonstrate our love for Jehovah
by patiently waiting on him
and respecting his sovereignty
エホバへの愛を表していきましょう
—his way of doing things.
If we do, we will enjoy
そうするなら 神が与えてくださる
この上ない平和を味わえます
the incomparable peace of God.
人事委員会の援助者
ラルフ･ウォールズ兄弟が
Now, Brother Ralph Walls,
a helper to the Personnel Committee,
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
will present the next talk of this symposium,
「愛があれば平和になる
隣人を愛する」
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love of Neighbor.”
終わりの時代によく見られる特徴を
予告したテモテ第二 3章には
Foretelling dominant traits
that would exist in the last days,
2 Timothy chapter 3 says
that “men will be lovers of themselves.”
「人々は自分を愛し」と書かれています
Is it wrong for us to love ourselves?
自分を愛するのは間違ったことですか
No, it’s normal, even necessary,
to have a healthy love of oneself.
いいえ 自分を適度に愛するのは普通で
必要なことでもあります
After all, Jesus said:
イエスも「隣人を自分自身のように
愛さなければならない」と言いました
“You must love your neighbor as yourself.”
これは後ほどさらに考えます
And we’ll talk more about that in a minute.
しかし 最初に述べた愛は
ゆがんだ自己中心的なものです
However, the love mentioned here
is distorted and selfish.
And because it prevents love of neighbor,
それによって隣人を愛するのが
難しくなるので 平和が妨げられます
it becomes a barrier to peace.
ある聖書学者たちによると
Some Bible scholars suggest that Paul
put love of self at the top of his list
パウロがテモテ第二 3:1-5で
at 2 Timothy 3:1-5
自分を愛することを最初に挙げたのは
because all the remaining
negative characteristics in the list
後に続く悪い性質全てが
そこから来ているからです
result from it.
そうした性質もやはり
平和を妨げるものとなります
And those traits too are a barrier to peace.
For example,
“not [being] open to any agreement”
例えば テモテ第二 3:3に
あるように
mentioned at 2 Timothy 3:3,
「全く人に同意しようと」しないなら
「怒り 憤り わめき 暴言など」に
つながることがあります
often leads to “anger, wrath,
screaming, and abusive speech.”
そのように自制心がないと
Rather than bringing peace,
such a lack of self-control
“stirs up strife.”
平和ではなく「争いを引き起こし」ます
On the other hand, love of neighbor
一方 隣人を愛するなら
has the opposite effect.
それと逆の結果
It leads to genuine peace.
本当の平和につながります
マタイ 22章をお開きください
Please turn to Matthew chapter 22,
36節を読みましょう
verse 36.
One of the Pharisees versed in the Law
律法に通じたパリサイ派の人が
イエスを試して言います
tests Jesus:
「先生 律法の中で
最も重要なおきてはどれですか」
“Teacher,
which is the greatest commandment
in the Law?”
前の話で詳しく取り上げられたように
Jesus responded with the words in verse 37
just considered at length
in the preceding talk:
イエスは37節でこう答えます
“You must love Jehovah your God.”
「あなたの神エホバを
愛さなければならない」
でもイエスは質問に答えるだけでなく
2つ目のおきても述べました
But then, Jesus goes
beyond the original question
and quotes a second commandment.
39節を読みましょう
Let’s read verse 39:
「第二も同様で こうです
“The second, like it, is this:
『あなたは隣人を自分自身のように
愛さなければならない』」
‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’”
イエスによると この2つのおきて
Jesus is saying that the two commandments
神への愛と隣人への愛は
つながっています
—love of God and love of neighbor—
are linked.
では「隣人」とは誰のことですか
Now, how exactly would you define “neighbor”?
どうぞルカ 10章をお開きください
Please turn to Luke chapter 10.
「私の隣人とはいったい誰でしょうか」
という質問に答え
Notice how Jesus answered this very question:
“Who really is my neighbor?”
イエスは 隣人として行動した
サマリア人の有名な例えを話します
Jesus responds clearly
with his renowned illustration
of the neighborly Samaritan.
In Jesus’ day, the Jews disdained Samaritans.
この例えの背景として
当時ユダヤ人はサマリア人を
軽蔑していました
Their attitude moved Jesus
to make a powerful point.
例えの中で サマリア人は
In his illustration,
Jesus said that the Samaritan
ユダヤ人の男性を助けるため
たくさんのことをしました
took extraordinary measures
to help a Jewish man.
ユダヤ人は強盗に襲われ
半殺しにされていましたが
The Jew had fallen victim to robbers,
and his own countrymen ignored him
仲間のユダヤ人は知らないふりをして
通り過ぎていきました
—leaving him half-dead.
イエスの話を聞いた人たちは
驚いたことでしょう
What Jesus said
must have stunned the audience.
ルカ 10:33, 34には
こうあります
Luke 10:33, 34 reads:
「ところが その道路を通っていた
あるサマリア人は
“But a certain Samaritan
“traveling the road came upon him,
そこに来て彼を見ると
かわいそうに思いました
“and at seeing him, he was moved with pity.
それで近寄り 傷に油とぶどう酒を
注いで包帯をしてあげました
“So he approached him
and bandaged his wounds,
“pouring oil and wine on them.
それから彼を自分の家畜に乗せ
“Then he mounted him on his own animal
and brought him to an inn
宿屋に連れていって世話をしました」
and took care of him.”
そして36節で イエスは
心を探る質問をします
Jesus then asked a penetrating question
in verse 36:
「この3人のうち誰が
強盗に襲われた人にとって
“Who of these three
seems to you
to have made himself neighbor?”
隣人になったと思いますか」
37節の言葉は今でも当てはまります
His words recorded in verse 37
are also directed to you and to me:
あなたにも 私にもです
“Go and do the same yourself.”
「行って あなたも
同じようにしなさい」
そうです 隣人とは家族や
クリスチャンの兄弟姉妹たちだけでなく
Yes, our neighbors include
not only our family members
and our Christian brothers and sisters
日常接する全ての人のことです
but all whom we encounter from day to day.
In other words, our love
それで私たちは
自分たちとは異なる人種 民族
国籍 宗教の人も愛します
extends to those who are not of our own race,
tribe, nationality, or religion.
How do we show that love?
その愛をどう示せますか
Please turn with me to Romans chapter 13.
ご一緒にローマ 13章を開きましょう
隣人を愛しているので
Because we love our neighbor,
we avoid conduct that disrupts peace.
平和を乱すようなことを
しないようにします
私たちはローマ 13:8-10にある
Instead, we strive to apply
the inspired counsel
at Romans 13:8-10:
神からのアドバイスを真剣に
当てはめるようにします
「誰に対しても義務を
負わないようにしましょう
“Do not owe anything to anyone
except to love one another;
ただし 愛し合うことは別です
“for whoever loves his fellow man
has fulfilled the law.
人を愛する人は律法を実践しています
『姦淫をしてはならない
“For the law code,
‘You must not commit adultery,
殺人をしてはならない
盗んではならない
“you must not murder,
you must not steal, you must not covet,’
貪欲になってはならない』という命令も
ほかのどんなおきても
“and whatever other commandment there is,
『隣人を自分自身のように
愛さなければならない』という言葉に
“is summed up in this saying:
“‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’
要約されるからです
愛があれば 隣人に対して
悪いことを行いません
“Love does not work evil to one’s neighbor;
ですから 愛があれば
律法を実践していることになるのです」
therefore, love is the law’s fulfillment.”
That means that our responsibility
is to treat others
それで 私たちには平和な仕方で
人に接する責任があります
in ways that promote peace.
不親切に扱われても
When others treat us unkindly,
we endeavor to imitate Jesus.
イエスに倣うよう努力します
イエスは侮辱されても仕返しをせず
When he was being insulted,
he did not return the insult.
苦しめられても相手を脅しませんでした
When he was suffering,
he didn’t go threatening.
平和の統治者と平和の神に倣うとき
Imitating the Prince of Peace
and the God of peace
gives us inner peace.
得られるのは心の平和です
In the following dramatization,
次のビデオを見て
ひどいことをされても隣人愛を示した
notice how a family benefits
from the apostle Paul’s example
of displaying love of neighbor,
使徒パウロの手本から学んでいる
家族に注目しましょう
even when provoked.
あんたは何やってんだよ 臆病者！
突っ立ってるだけじゃないか
What are you going to do?
You’re just a coward.
Man, all you do
is stand next to your little cart.
中立？ そんなのないんだよ！臆病者！
突っ立ってるだけじゃないか 臆病者！
You don’t do anything.
You’re just a coward.
You just stand next to your little cart.
Ain’t no neutral.
こっちは自分たちの権利のために
もっとやってるんだ！ 臆病者！
Stand up for your rights.
You’re just a coward.
Gabe,
ガブリエル 今日何があったの？
what happened today?
It’s just that I’ve been yelled at
in service before, but
前にも伝道で
怒鳴られたことはあったけど
今日はほんとにもう
this time I wanted to—I don’t know.
なんて言うか・・・
I wanted to go up to the girls
and smash their phones.
あの子たちの所に行って
携帯壊したかった
しなくてよかった
I’m so glad that you didn’t.
Yeah, but
うん でも
I feel guilty
ちょっと後悔してる
because I was like—I was like so angry.
なんか すっごい腹が立っちゃって
It’s OK.
大丈夫よ
続きを読みましょう
Let’s keep reading.
We had left off in verse 26.
26節からだったわね
“Suddenly a great earthquake occurred,
「突然 大きな地震が起きて
“so that the foundations of the jail
were shaken.
牢屋が土台から揺れた
“Moreover, all the doors
were instantly opened,
その上 全ての戸が直ちに開き
“and everyone’s bonds came loose.
皆の鎖やかせが外れた
“When the jailer woke up
and saw that the prison doors were open,
牢番は目を覚まして牢屋の戸が
開いているのを見ると
“he drew his sword
囚人たちが逃げてしまったものと思い
“and was about to kill himself,
剣を抜いて自殺しようとした
“assuming that the prisoners had escaped.
しかしパウロは大声で
“But Paul called out with a loud voice:
『やめなさい 皆ここにいます！』と
叫んだ
“‘Do not hurt yourself, for we are all here!’
牢番は明かりを持ってこさせてから
“So he asked for lights and rushed in,
中に駆け込み
“and seized with trembling,
震えながら
パウロとシラスの前にひれ伏した」
he fell down before Paul and Silas.”
地震の前 牢番が
パウロにした仕打ちを考えて
Now, think about what the jailer
had done to Paul.
牢番を憎んでも仕方がなかったよね
He could have hated him for it.
Yeah, he could have.
うん でもそうしなかった
But I guess he saw the jailer’s pain
instead of just his own.
きっと 自分のことより
牢番の気持ちを考えたんだと思う
パウロは隣人を愛していて
Yeah, Paul loved his neighbor.
He didn’t hold back
from trying to save his life.
命を助けようとしたんだ
Come on, man.
ちょっと来て
Hey, how do you have the nerve
to keep coming out here?
おい なんでまたここに立ってんだよ？
この間言ってたこと
その通りだと思いました
Look, you were right
about what you said.
不公正を見ながら何も
しないっていうのは良くありませんよね
No one should stand around
while other people suffer injustice.
So do something. Fight like we do.
だったら俺たちみたいに行動しろよ
This is my way of making a difference
私は 別の方法で世界が変わると考えて
活動しているんです
—the only way that I know
the world can really change.
Come on, man, the Bible?
その方法が聖書か？
Look, I get what you’re thinking,
but let me show you just one scripture.
そういうイメージないかもしれませんが
1つだけ見ていただけますか
All right, one scripture.
1つだけな
私はこの言葉を読んで
こういう活動をしようと思ったんです
So this is a verse in the Bible
that convinced me
of how I can make a difference.
It’s at Matthew 24:14.
マタイ 24:14です
Here it says:
「そして 王国の良い知らせは
“And this good news of the Kingdom
will be preached
全ての国の人々が聞けるように
“in all the inhabited earth
世界中で伝えられます
“for a witness to all the nations,
and then the end will come.”
それから終わりが来ます」
ビデオの中の場面で
In the dramatization, Paul could have reacted
パウロは牢番に復讐することも
できたでしょう
in a negative way toward the jailer.
でも ひどい仕打ちを
受けたにもかかわらず
However, in spite of the way
he had been treated,
he displayed neighborly love.
隣人愛を示しました
これは牢番に大きな影響を与え
And this had a powerful effect on the jailer
エホバへの賛美につながりました
and brought praise to Jehovah.
私たちは不完全なので
Because we are imperfect,
隣人愛を育てるため
we must work hard
at cultivating love for our neighbor.
懸命に努力しなければなりません
This is illustrated in what happened
with the apostle Peter.
使徒ペテロに起きたことが
これをよく示しています
Prior to becoming a follower of Jesus,
ペテロはイエスの弟子になる前
ユダヤ人でない人と
交友を持ちませんでした
he did not have fellowship
with non-Jewish people.
でもクリスチャンになった後
But after he became a Christian,
God taught him
神からユダヤ人と異国人の間の壁は
取り除かれたと教えられ
that division between Jews and Gentiles
was not to continue,
それを理解しました
and Peter got the point.
使徒 10:34, 35で
At Acts 10:34, 35,
ペテロはこう言っています
Peter is quoted as saying:
「神が不公平ではないことが
よく分かりました
“Now I truly understand
that God is not partial,
神を畏れて正しいことを行う人は
“but in every nation the man who fears him
and does what is right
どの国の人でも
神に受け入れられるのです」
is acceptable to him.”
ペテロはクリスチャンになった
異国人の家に何日かとどまり
Peter even stayed in the newly converted
Gentiles’ home for days.
And he continued the practice of eating
その後もユダヤ人でない
クリスチャンたちと食事をしていました
with non-Jewish Christians.
しかし13年後
However, 13 years later
シリアのアンティオキアにいる時
while in Syrian Antioch,
ペテロは突然 異国人の
クリスチャンとの交友をやめます
Peter suddenly stopped associating
with Gentile Christians.
Why?
変化を受け入れないユダヤ人の
クリスチャンの反応を恐れたのです
He feared the reaction
of some Jewish Christians
who were slow to accept change.
偏見というのが根深いもので
あることが分かります
This illustrates that prejudice
can be deeply rooted.
取り除くには努力し続け
なければなりません
It takes constant effort
to rid ourselves of it.
他の人に対してエホバのような
公平な見方を持つ必要があります
But we must learn to view others impartially
as Jehovah does.
エホバのように他の人に接しましょう
We want to treat others
as Jehovah treats them.
イエスは言いました
In his Sermon on the Mount, Jesus said:
「あなたたちは
こう命じられたのを知っています
“You heard that it was said:
“‘You must love your neighbor
and hate your enemy.’
『隣人を愛し 敵を
憎まなければならない』
しかし私は言います
“However, I say to you:
敵を愛し続け
“Continue to love your enemies
迫害する人のために祈り続けなさい」
and to pray for those who persecute you.”
それから山上の垂訓の続きの
Then, as recorded at Matthew chapter 5,
マタイ 5:45に記されているように
and verse 45,
そうした愛を示す理由を説明します
he explains why we want to show
that type of love:
“So that you may prove yourselves
sons of your Father who is in the heavens,
「自分が天にいる父の子で
あることを示すためです
父は悪人にも善人にも太陽を昇らせ
“since he makes his sun rise
on both the wicked and the good
正しい人にも正しくない人にも
“and makes it rain on both the righteous
雨を降らせてくださるのです」
and the unrighteous.”
This love produced by holy spirit
聖なる力が生み出すこの愛は
is markedly different from the sort of love
that is common in the world.
世の中で広く見られる愛と
大きく違います
より高い原則に基づいています
It’s based on a higher principle.
イエスは 罪人でさえ良くしてくれる人
には良くすると言いました
Jesus said even sinners
will follow a policy of like for like.
でも 私たちは「天にいる
父の子であることを示すため」
But if we want to prove ourselves
sons of our “Father who is in the heavens,”
違っていなければなりません
we must be different.
神とキリストが迎え入れて
くださったように
We welcome others
私たちも他の人を迎え入れます
as God and Christ have welcomed us.
ローマ 15:7はこう勧めています
At Romans 15:7, the Bible says to us:
「キリストが皆さんを
迎え入れてくださったように
“Welcome one another,
just as Christ also welcomed you.”
互いを迎え入れてください」
ここのギリシャ語が言っているのは
The Greek word used there conveys the idea
家や友達の輪に迎え入れるなど
of receiving someone kindly or hospitably
親切にまた手厚く迎えるということです
—such as into one’s home
or circle of friends.
愛が育てば偏見は枯れていくのです
Prejudice withers as love grows.
Remember that at one time,
私たちは皆かつて いわばよそ者で
we were all strangers, or foreigners,
not close to God.
神から遠く離れていました
でもエホバは「愛の綱」で
私たちを引き寄せてくださいました
But Jehovah drew us to him
with “cords of love.”
Christ welcomed us.
キリストが迎え入れてくださいました
いわばドアを開いて神の家族に
加われるようにしてくれました
He opened the door, as it were,
so that we could become part of God’s family.
イエスが不完全な私たちを
Since Jesus has kindly accepted us
親切に迎え入れてくださったのですから
as imperfect as we are,
私たちが誰かを退けることなど
考えられません
it should be unthinkable for us
to reject anyone else.
Dear brothers and sisters,
愛する兄弟姉妹の皆さん
divisions, prejudice, and hostility
will doubtless increase in the world
この邪悪な体制の終わりが近づくにつれ
分裂 偏見 敵意は増していきます
as we approach the end of this wicked system.
でもエホバに仕える私たちは
As servants of Jehovah, though,
「天からの知恵」に従い
差別をしたりせず
we seek “the wisdom from above,”
which is impartial
平和を求めます
and promotes peace.
We rejoice
私たちは喜んで
as we forge friendships
with people from other lands,
ほかの国の人々との友情を育んで
文化の違いを受け入れ
accept cultural differences,
できるならその人たちの言語を学びます
and possibly even learn
the languages of others.
そうするとき 平和は
「川の流れのように」豊かに
When we do this,
peace flows “just like a river”
公正は「海の波のように」
豊かになります
and justice “like the waves of the sea.”
私たちは「全ての人に
特に⋯⋯兄弟姉妹に
We “work what is good toward all,
善いことを行い」ます
but especially [our brothers].”
隣人への愛に動かされて
Love of neighbor moves us
to make sacrifices in behalf of others
他の人のために犠牲を払い
あらゆる機会に良い知らせを伝えます
and to share the good news
at every opportunity.
私たちの主人イエスは言いました
Our Master, Jesus, said:
「私があなたたちを愛した通りに
“This is my commandment,
that you love one another
just as I have loved you.”
あなたたちが互いを愛すること
これが私のおきてです」
隣人を愛することによって
どんな良いことがありますか
What are the blessings
that come from love of neighbor?
ヨハネ 15章でイエスが答えています
Jesus answers that
at John chapter 15,
8-10節を読みましょう
and we’ll read verses 8 through 10,
まず8節です
beginning with verse 8.
Number one:
1つ目 「あなたたちが
多くの実を結び続け
“My father is glorified in this,
私の弟子であることを示すことによって
“that you keep bearing much fruit
私の父は称賛を受けます」
and prove yourselves my disciples.”
The second blessing, verse 9:
2つ目 9節
「父が私を愛したように
私はあなたたちを愛しました
“Just as the Father has loved me,
so I have loved you;
“remain in my love.
いつも私に愛されるようにしていなさい
“If you observe my commandments,
私のおきてを守るなら
いつも私に愛されます
“you will remain in my love,
私が父のおきてを守っていつも父に
愛されるようにしているのと同じです」
“just as I have observed
the commandments of the Father
and remain in his love.”
執筆委員会の援助者
ロバート･シランコ兄弟が
Brother Robert Ciranko,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present the final talk
of this symposium,
このシンポジウムの最後の話をします
主題は「愛があれば平和になる
聖書を愛する」です
“How Love Leads to Genuine Peace
—Love for God’s Word.”
Can you imagine a collection
of some 40 million books?
4000万冊もの本が並んでいるのを
想像できますか
They would fill more than 800 miles,
これは1300キロにおよぶ本棚を
埋め尽くすほどの数です
or 1,300 kilometers, of bookshelves?
And yet, that is what you can find
in what has been described
米国ワシントンDCにある
議会図書館の話です
as the largest library in the world
世界最大の図書館
といわれるその場所には
—the Library of Congress
in Washington, D.C.,
それだけの数の本があります
in the United States.
その中で一番読む価値がある本は
と聞かれたら何と答えますか
Which book would you say
is the most worthwhile to read
among all of those millions of volumes?
使徒パウロに答えてもらいましょう
We can let the apostle Paul
answer that question.
パウロは
テモテへの第二の手紙 3:15で
In his second letter to Timothy
at 2 Timothy 3:15,
he referred to “the holy writings,
which are able to make [us]
「聖なる書物⋯⋯はあなたを賢くし
キリスト･イエスへの信仰による救いを
得られるようにします」と言っています
wise for salvation
through faith in Christ Jesus.”
He was referring, of course,
to God’s own written Word
パウロが言っていたのは
神ご自身の言葉 聖書のことでした
that we know as the Bible.
聖書は救いを得るのに必要な
知恵を与えてくれるので
The contents of this book can give us
the wisdom that we need to gain salvation,
世界で一番価値のある本です
and that makes it
the most worthwhile book on earth.
本というものにそれほどの
力があるのでしょうか
But how can a book have
such a profound effect on a person?
本とその著者との関係について
Well, when describing books
and their authors per se,
ギルバート・ハイエットという
作家がこう述べています
the secular writer Gilbert Highet once stated
「本というのは命のない紙の束ではなく
that books are not “lumps of lifeless paper,
“but minds alive on the shelves.
本棚に並ぶ生きた知性である
それぞれが声を発している⋯⋯
“From each of them goes out
its own voice . . .
“So by taking down one of these volumes
and opening it,
それで1冊手に取って開くと
著者の声が時間と空間を
超えて聞こえてくる
“one can call into range
the voice of a man the author,
そして 著者の考えや気持ちが
“far distant in time and space,
and hear him speaking to us,
mind to mind, heart to heart.”
私たちの考えや気持ちに影響を与える」
本棚からこの本 聖書を
取り出して開くと
When we take this book, the Bible,
down off the shelf and open it,
その著者であるエホバの声が
聞こえてきます
we are calling into range
the voice of its Author, Jehovah.
And is he speaking to us
mind to mind, heart to heart?
エホバの考えや気持ちも
伝わってきますか
Indeed, he is.
その通りです
For example, at Jeremiah 29:11,
Jehovah tells us:
エホバは エレミヤ 29:11で
こう言っています
「私は あなたたちのために
“I well know the thoughts
that I am thinking toward you, . . .
自分が行おうとしていることを
よく知っている⋯⋯
“thoughts of peace, and not of calamity,
良い将来と希望を
与えたいと思っている」
to give you a future and a hope.”
格言 27:11ではこう言っています
And at Proverbs 27:11, Jehovah tells us:
「賢くあって 私の心を喜ばせよ
“Be wise . . . and make my heart rejoice,
so that I can make a reply
to him who taunts me.”
私をあざける者に
私が答えるためである」
How grateful we are
that Jehovah has given us
エホバが聖書という貴重な本を
与えてくださったことに感謝できます
his precious Word, the Bible,
それによって エホバの
考えや気持ちを知り
that reveals his intimate thoughts
and feelings,
that draws us close to him,
エホバに近づき 永遠の命を
得る方法を学べます
and that teaches us
how to gain everlasting life!
私たちはエホバを愛しているので
Because we love Jehovah,
we also love and cherish
聖書を通してエホバが言われることも
愛し大切にします
what he tells us
through the pages of his written Word.
And that is exactly how the psalmist felt
詩編 119編の作者は
who wrote the 119th Psalm.
まさにそのように感じていました
Please open your Bible to Psalm 119,
どうぞ聖書の詩編 119編を開いて
161節をご覧ください
and find verse 161.
詩編 119:161の
後半にこうあります
That’s Psalm 119:161.
In the latter part, it says:
「しかし私の心が畏れるのは
あなたの言葉」
“But my heart stands in awe of your words.”
さらに167節と168節も
読みましょう
Now see what more he wrote
in verses 167 and 168:
「あなたの教えを守り こよなく愛する
“I keep your reminders,
and I love them dearly.
あなたの命令と教えを守る
“I observe your orders and your reminders,
私がすることをあなたは
全て知っている」
for you are aware of all that I do.”
この聖書筆者は 神の命令と教えを
This Bible writer did not view
God’s orders and reminders
単に冷たい法律を並べたもの
とは見ませんでした
as just a list of cold, legalistic statutes.
And we can be sure
that he did not consider them
それを重荷とも考えなかったに
違いありません
to be burdensome.
それが最高の生き方をする
土台となるということを知っていました
Instead, he knew that they formed the basis
for the best life possible.
それで 神の命令と教えを
学ぶだけでなく
And that is why he not only wanted
to learn God’s orders,
それを守りたいという願いも
持っていました
but he also desired to observe,
or obey, them.
この詩編から分かるように
神の言葉こそ学ぶ価値があり
The psalmist believed that God’s Word
is the one thing worth studying,
and that because of knowing
God’s orders and reminders,
神の命令と教えを知っていれば
それ以外の全てのことを
知っている人より
we are far wiser than people
who know everything else
except God’s Word.
はるかに賢くなることができます
Now look at what more he wrote in verse 165:
165節にも注目しましょう
165節
「豊かな平和はあなたの律法を
愛する人たちのもの
“Abundant peace
belongs to those who love your law;
その人たちはどんなものにも
つまずかない」
nothing can make them stumble.”
これが聖書を愛する大きな理由です
Herein lies a major reason
why we love God’s Word:
それに従えば平和になるということです
Abiding by it leads to genuine peace.
誰もが平和を願っていますが
Everyone longs for peace in their life,
どうすればそれを得られるか
and through the pages of the Bible,
we learn how to attain it.
聖書から分かります
それで 聖書に従うことを選び
That is why we choose to live by God’s Word
試練に直面するとしてもそうします
even in the face of the trials
that arise in our life
試練によって心の平和が
奪われそうになる時もです
—some of which may try to steal away
our peace of mind and heart.
エホバは 私たちが毎日の生活で
経験することをご存じで
And yet, Jehovah knows what we
are going through every day of our lives
and stands ready to help us.
助けてくださいます
エホバの言葉を愛してそれに従うなら
If we love and obey Jehovah’s Word,
we will not be stumbled spiritually
by what someone else does or says
人の言動や生活で生じる
他の事柄によって
つまずくこと 信仰を
妨げられることはありません
or by any other matter or situation in life.
聖書への愛があれば どのように
平和になり それを保てますか
But how does love for God’s Word
lead to such peace
and keep us from stumbling?
「聖書全体は神の聖なる力の
導きによって書かれた」ので
We know
that “all scripture is inspired of God,”
making the Bible the most reliable guide
for every aspect of life.
どんな場面でも役に立ちます
神は私たちよりはるかに知恵のある方で
After all, his wisdom
is infinitely superior to our own.
聖書を読むと 物事を神の高い観点で
見ることができます
Reading the Bible enables us
to look at matters
from God’s elevated point of view.
It is just as the prophet Isaiah wrote
預言者イザヤが
イザヤ 55:8, 9で
at Isaiah 55:8, 9.
書いた通りです どうぞ
イザヤ 55:8, 9を
お開きください
If you’d like to open to that, please
—Isaiah 55:8, 9.
こうあります
He wrote: “‘For my thoughts
are not your thoughts,
「私の考えはあなたたちの考えとは違い
あなたたちの行いは私の行いとは違う
“and your ways are not my ways,’
declares Jehovah.
天が地より高いように 私の行いは
あなたたちの行いより高く
“‘For as the heavens
are higher than the earth,
“‘so my ways are higher than your ways
私の考えはあなたたちの考えより高い」
and my thoughts than your thoughts.’”
どうですか エホバの考えや言葉は
Just imagine
—Jehovah’s thoughts and language
must be vastly superior to those of humans.
人間よりはるかに優れているのです
エホバは聖書を通して人間と
コミュニケーションを取る時
When he communicates with us,
as he does through the pages of the Bible,
he simplifies how he expresses his thoughts
人間が理解できるようにご自分の
考えを分かりやすく表現されます
so that we can understand them.
エホバの言うことを取り入れていくと
Then as we take in all that Jehovah says,
自分の考えをエホバの考えに
合わせられます
we can let his thinking guide our thinking.
聖書を読むのは鏡を見るようなものです
Reading the Bible
can be likened to peering into a mirror
聖書の言葉によって 自分が
本当にどんな人かを見ることができ
because its message
has the power to allow us
to see ourselves as we really are
自分の態度や行いのどこを調整
したらいいかが分かるからです
and it shows us where adjustments
are needed
in our attitude and conduct.
これがどう役立つかを
このシンポジウムで見てきました
Thus far in this symposium,
we have seen how this can actually work.
We have seen two dramatizations
of a widowed mother
2つのビデオで やもめの母親は
自分の10代の子供たちが
using the Bible to help her teenage children
avoid being stumbled
ほかの若者から圧力を
受けても屈しないよう
by other young people
who had been harassing them.
聖書を使って助けていました
息子のガブリエルは
公共エリア伝道の時に
Remember, her son, Gabe,
had been called a coward
by a couple of tough-looking youths
いかつい若者たちから
臆病者と言われていました
while he was engaged in public witnessing.
娘のオリビアは クラスの男子と
デートをする気がないことで
And her daughter, Olivia,
had been chided by other girls
for not being interested in dating
one of the guys in her class.
ほかの女子からいじめられていました
Their mother used what Jehovah inspired
the apostle Paul to write about
とても難しい状況でどのように
平和を保てるかについて
母親は 聖なる力の
導きによって書かれた
with his ordeal in prison
to show how he was able
to preserve his peace
使徒パウロの投獄に関する
記述を使って教えていました
in a very difficult situation.
それはオリビアとガブリエルにとって
And that, in turn, helped Olivia and Gabe
to safeguard their own peace.
とても役立つ内容でした
では娘が平和を失うような
行いを避けるよう
Let’s see what more the mother finds
in the Bible to help Olivia
母親が聖書の別の記述を使って
どのように助けるか見てみましょう
avoid being stumbled into conduct
that could rob her of peace.
Guess who just walked in?
来た来た 誰だと思う？ オリビアです
Olivia.
And there’s Jake.
で ジェイク
オリビアはジェイクとすると思う？
Would she ever?
You know she’s wild.
ほんとはすごいんだから
男子に興味あんの？
I don’t even think she likes guys.
What if she’s into girls?
I bet she’s still a virgin.
レズなんじゃない？
まだ未経験なんじゃないの？
Olivia, what are you thinking?
オリビア 大丈夫？
I don’t—I don’t know how they could do that.
なんで なんでこんなことするのか
分かんない
I don’t even follow them.
別に仲良くもないのに
If this doesn’t stop,
また同じことされたら
I don’t know if I can . . .
どうしたらいいか・・・
You’re strong, OK.
きっと大丈夫
頑張れる強さを持ってるじゃない
You just can’t let them get to you.
自分ではどうにも
できないように思うよね
It feels out of your control, doesn’t it?
Hey, I think we need another Bible example.
ねえ 聖書の別の話を
思い出したんだけど
Remember when we studied
about the Shulammite girl?
シュラムの乙女について勉強したの
覚えてる？
うん 覚えてる
Yeah, I remember.
And who was pressuring her?
誰がアプローチしてきた？
Solomon.
ソロモン
でも彼女にその気はなかった
But she wasn’t interested in him,
just like I’m not interested
in that boy Jake, so . . .
私がジェイクに興味がないのと同じで
でもソロモンだけじゃなかったわね
But it wasn’t just him;
there were the daughters of Jerusalem
in Solomon’s court.
ソロモンの宮廷にいた女性たちも
They urged her to accept his attentions.
ソロモンの申し出を
受け入れるよう言ってきた
But do you remember what she said
でもなんて答えたんだっけ？
in Song of Solomon chapter 2?
「ソロモンの歌」2章
It says: “I put you under oath,
「エルサレムの女性たち
“O daughters of Jerusalem,
皆さんはガゼルや野の雌鹿の
美しさが分かる女性
“by the gazelles and the does of the field:
“Do not try to awaken or arouse love in me
誓ってください
私の愛を無理に呼び起こさないと」
until it feels inclined.”
いろんな圧力があって
彼女は圧力に負けちゃったかしら？
So despite all of the pressure,
who was really in control?
She was.
負けなかった
誰に何を言われても
No one was going to push her
into something that she didn’t want to do.
言いなりにはならなかった
She even said: “I am a wall.”
「私は城壁」とも言っているわね
あなたも同じように強くなれるわよ
You have the same power.
And if you believe that,
it’ll change how you handle the pressure.
そう思っていれば
気持ちを強く持って行動できるわね
Now give me a hug.
あなたならできる
Hey, guys, update on yesterday’s topic.
ねえみんな きのうの続き
オリビアはまだジェイクと
やってないみたい
I guess she still needs a man.
She needs something.
オリビア彼氏募集中
I just posted it. Go like my video.
動画アップしたよ いいね押してね
All they want is to see me give in.
自分たちと同じことを
させようとしてるだけなんだ
ねえみんな きのうの続き
Hey, guys, update on yesterday’s topic.
I guess she still needs . . .
オリビアはまだジェイクと
やってないみたい
Why would I give them the satisfaction?
私はあの子たちの言いなりにはならない
My peace comes from doing the right thing.
正しいことをしていれば
平和な気持ちでいられる
Nobody can make me stumble.
私は屈しない
「私は城壁」
“I am a wall.”
Olivia’s mother thought
of another inspired Bible example,
母親はシュラムの乙女の
手本を思い出しました
that of the Shulammite girl
who was being urged
その乙女はソロモンの
申し出を受け入れるよう
by the young women in Solomon’s court
to accept his amorous attentions.
宮廷の女性たちから圧力を受けました
But despite the pressure,
the Shulammite girl remained in control
でもシュラムの乙女はほかの人の
言いなりになったりせず
したくないことをさせようとする
圧力に負けませんでした
for no one was going to push her
into something that she did not want to do.
Olivia got the point
as she thought to herself:
オリビアは要点を理解して言いました
「正しいことをしていれば
平和な気持ちでいられる
‘My peace comes from doing the right thing.
Nobody can make me stumble. I am a wall.’
私は屈しない 私は城壁」
明らかに母親は聖書を本当に愛し
It’s obvious that the mother
had a real love for God’s Word, knew it well,
よく知っていて 圧力に屈しないよう
子供たちの考えを導くために
and calmly and skillfully used it
to guide the thinking of her children
聖書を穏やかに上手に使っていました
to keep them from stumbling.
今では多くの人が聖書のことなど
お構いなしで見向きもしません
So many people these days
put God’s Word out of their mind
to prevent it from influencing their life.
でも モラルが低下しても
私たちは聖書にしっかり従って
But as the world’s morals decline,
we must stick loyally to God’s Word
to conform our conduct
to his pure and holy thinking
神の聖なる考えに沿って行動し
神の基準に従う決意を
強めなければなりません
and strengthen our determination
to live by his standards.
これはまさにローマ 12:2で
使徒パウロが勧めている点です
That is just what the apostle Paul
urged us to do
at Romans 12:2.
ご一緒にローマ 12:2の
言葉を読みましょう
If you would turn there, please
—Romans 12:2.
こうあります
Paul wrote:
「そして 今の体制によって
形作られるのをやめてください
“And stop being molded
by this system of things,
“but be transformed
by making your mind over,
かえって 考え方を新しくする
ことによって自分を変化させましょう
“so that you may prove to yourselves
the good and acceptable
それは 神の善い意志 喜ばしい
完全な意志を見極めるためです」
and perfect will of God.”
God’s Word strengthens us
to resist conforming
聖書から力を得て 世に抵抗し
to the corrupting practices of Satan’s world
堕落した習慣を退け
and to suppress temptations
toward wrongdoing.
自分を制して悪い行いを
しないようにしましょう
Now, as we prove to ourselves
私たちは神の善い意志
that the will of God is good and perfect,
完全な意志を見極めると
then we should also accept
神にしっかり従うのが最善の生き方で
あることも認めるようになります
that loyally obeying God
is the best way of living.
聖書の教えを生活の中で
当てはめることは
There is a direct connection
between heeding Scriptural teachings
and obeying or enjoying genuine peace.
必ず真の平和という結果につながります
でもエホバの言葉が
生活に影響を及ぼすには
However, for Jehovah’s Word
to have such power in our lives,
聖書を毎日読んで
we need to read the Bible every day
そのアドバイスがなぜためになるかを
じっくり考える必要があります
and meditate on why its counsel
is beneficial.
That means reading it at a pace
読んでいる内容を
じっくり考えられるペースで
that allows us to ponder
on what we are reading.
読まなければならないということです
And doing this helps to fix in our minds
the portions
大切な点を記憶にとどめるのに
それは役立ちます
that are especially helpful to us.
ある兄弟は 聖書を毎日読む理由を
尋ねられてこう答えました
When asked why he reads the Bible
every day,
one Christian replied:
「日中 何度もエホバに祈り
“If I repeatedly pray to Jehovah
during the day
それを聞いてくださるよう
期待するのであれば
“and expect him to hear me,
自分も毎日聖書を読んで
“why shouldn’t I also listen to God
by reading his Word every day?
神の言葉に耳を傾けるべきだと思います
良い友でいたければ こちらばかりが
話すことはないはずです」
“If we want to be a good friend,
why would we do all the talking?”
He makes a very good point, doesn’t he?
確かにその通りですね
聖書を読むなら
エホバの声を聞くことができ
By reading the Bible,
we are listening to Jehovah,
そのようにしてエホバの見方を
学ぶことができます
and that is how we get
his viewpoint on matters.
では 毎日神に話して
いただくようにしていますか
So do you allow God
to speak to you every day?
聖書通読の効果性は
We can measure
how effective our Bible reading is
自分の態度や行いに与える
影響で測れます
by the influence it has
on our attitude and conduct.
平和が乱される時
神の知恵と導きを求めて
When our peace is disturbed,
we can look into the source of divine wisdom
聖書を調べましょう
for God’s guidance.
天に行くクリスチャンについて
Speaking prophetically of anointed Christians
イザヤ 54:13は
こう預言しています
at Isaiah 54:13, the prophet wrote:
「あなたの子たちは皆エホバに教えられ
“All your sons will be taught by Jehovah,
豊かな平和を味わう」
and [their] peace . . . will be abundant.”
この描写は キリストの
ほかの羊にも当てはまります
Now, those words apply in principle
to Christ’s other sheep as well.
Thankfully, when Christ’s anointed brothers,
“the faithful and discreet slave,”
感謝すべきことに キリストの兄弟
である「忠実で思慮深い奴隷」は
prepare spiritual food for us,
such as this convention program,
この大会を含め 私たちを教える時
they hold firmly to Jehovah’s Word
and they never water it down.
聖書にしっかり従い その教えを
曖昧にしたりはしません
We always receive spiritual instruction
私たちが受ける教えはいつも
that upholds Jehovah’s high moral standards,
エホバの高い道徳基準に沿ったもので
エホバの教えを受け入れる時
and we are blessed with abundant peace
豊かな平和を味わうことができます
when we accept Jehovah’s instruction.
イザヤが書いた別の預言も
今日実現しています
Isaiah penned another prophecy
that is being fulfilled today,
and we find that at Isaiah 2:2-4.
イザヤ 2:2-4です
終わりの時代の幻の中で
He saw in a vision of the last days
全ての国の人々がエホバを崇拝します
people from all the nations
streaming to true worship.
And for what reason?
なぜでしょうか
イザヤはこう書いています
Isaiah wrote of Jehovah:
「神はご自分の道について
教えてくださる
“He will instruct us about his ways,
and we will walk in his paths.”
私たちはその道を歩もう」
And in what would this result?
どんな結果になりますか
こうあります
So that “they will beat their swords
into plowshares
「彼らは剣をすきに
やりを鎌に作り替える
“and their spears into pruning shears.
“Nation will not lift up sword
against nation,
国は国に向かって剣を振り上げず
nor will they learn war anymore.”
彼らはもはや戦いを学ばない」
善い神であるエホバは
不完全である私たちに
In his goodness, Jehovah is willing
to teach us imperfect humans
世界中で本当の平和を実現する
方法を教えてくださっています
how to achieve genuine,
abundant peace earth wide.
And he does that through the pages
of his own written Word.
ご自分の言葉である聖書を通してです
神に教えられるのは
本当に素晴らしいことです
What a privilege it is
to be taught by our God!
何かの問題が起きて
No matter what problem may threaten
the peace of our personal life,
個人 家族 会衆の平和が
脅かされるとしても
our family, or our congregation,
聖書に解決策があると確信できます
we are confident that the solution
can be found in the Bible.
このシンポジウムで学んだように
And as we have learned from this symposium,
エホバと隣人と聖書への
愛を持ち続けるなら
our continued love for Jehovah,
for our neighbor, and for God’s Word
神の新しい世界で
will lead to our enjoying everlasting peace
永遠に平和を味わうことが
できるでしょう
in God’s new world.
兄弟たち ありがとうございました
Thank you, brothers, for teaching us
how love motivates our pursuit of peace.
愛があれば平和を
つくれることが分かりました
ではここで歌を歌って
Each of us now has an opportunity
to praise Jehovah with song.
エホバを賛美することにしましょう
24番の「エホバの山に登ろう」
という歌をご一緒に歌いましょう
We will sing song number 24, entitled
“Come to Jehovah’s Mountain.”
That’s song number 24.
24番です